[Woman] Miss Carmichael, please.
Dr. Petersen is ready for you.
Awfully sorry I have to go.
Had a perfect hand.
- Would have beaten the pants off you.
- Harry will take you.
- Oh, thank you.
- [Whispering] Watch her carefully.
Don't take your eyes off her.
- How are you today, Harry?
- Fine.
- You look a little bilious.
- It's the light.
- I worry about you, dear.
- I'll be all right.
Must we dash
into Dr. Petersen's office?
Can't we go sit somewhere
in private and talk, just you and I?
Love it, if I had time.
Would you?
[Giggles]
[Gasps, Sighs]
- [Doorbell Buzzes]
- Come in.
You ruined a very interesting
card game, Dr. Petersen.
- You may go now, Harry.
- I'll be outside.
- [Door Closes]
- I hope you feel better today, Mary.
- Well, I don't.
- You will.
I think this whole
thing is ridiculous.
- What whole thing, Mary?
- Psychoanalysis.
It bores the pants off me.
Lying on the couch like some
dreary nitwit telling all.
You don't really expect to get
anywhere listening to me babble
- Really!
- My patients invariably regard me...
as a wretched nuisance
during our first talks.
I see. It's my subconscious
putting up a fight.
- It doesn't want me cured.
- Exactly.
It wants to continue
enjoying your disease.
Our job is to make you
understand why.
When you know why you're doing
something that's bad for you and
why, then you can begin
curing yourself.
- You mean I've been telling you lies.
- The usual proportion.
You're right.
I'm lying like mad.
I hate men.
I loathe them.
If one of them
so much as touches me...
I want to sink my teeth
into his hand and bite it off.
Hmm. In fact, I did that once.
Would you care to hear about it?
- Tell me anything you remember.
- We were dancing.
He kept asking me to marry him,
panting in my ear.
I suddenly pretended
I was going to kiss him.
I sank my teeth
into his moustache.
Bit it clear off.
You're laughing at me.
That smug, frozen face
of yours doesn't take me in.
You just want me to tell you all this
so you can feel superior to me.
You and your drooling science.
I detest you!
I never want to see that
nasty face of yours again!
I can't bear you!
You and your nickel's worth of nothing!
[Sobbing]
Come on, Miss Carmichael.
Silly fool. Letting a creature
like that worry me. Miss Frozen-puss.
Oh, Dr. Fleurot,
I want to talk to you alone.
I can't stand that woman.
- I'll see you later, Mary.
- Come, Miss Carmichael.
[Moans]
Murchison must be really out of his mind
to assign Carmichael to you.
You may report your findings
to the new head when he arrives.
You can't treat
a love veteran like Carmichael
I have done a great deal
of research on emotional problems
Research, my eye!
I've watched your work
for six months.
It's brilliant but lifeless.
There's no intuition in it.
You approach all your problems
with an ice pack on your head.
- Are you making love to me?
- I will in a moment.
I'm just clearing
the ground first.
I'm trying to convince you
that your lack of human
is bad for you as a doctor...
and fatal for you as a woman.
I've heard that argument from
a number of amorous psychiatrists...
who all wanted to make
a better doctor of me.
Ah, but I've got
a much better argument.
- I'm terribly fond of you.
- Why?
It's rather like
embracing a textbook.
- But why do you do it, then?
- Because you're not a textbook.
You're a sweet, pulsing,
adorable woman underneath.
I sense it every time
I come near to you.
You sense only your own
desires and pulsations.
I assure you, mine
in no way resemble them.
Stop it.
I'm mad about you.
I'm afraid I'm boring you.
No. Your attitudes
are very interesting.
I feel exactly
like Miss Carmichael.
I'd like to throw a book
at you... but I won't.
- May I borrow this?
- Certainly.
Oh, and forgive me for my criticism.
I think you'd better stick to books.
Oh, and another thing...
Pardon me for marching in,
but I'm spreading the tidings.
My successor
will be due any moment.
- Well, Dr. Murchison, it's been
a pleasure working under you.
[Fleurot]
Coming, Dr. Petersen?
Oh, I'm in no mad hurry
to welcome Dr. Edwardes.
It's hard to imagine this place
without you, Dr. Murchison.
Yes, I sort of go
with the fixtures.
More than that.
You are Green Manors. It seems unfair.
You're very young
in the profession.
You haven't learned
the basic secret of science.
The old must make way
for the new.
Particularly when the old is suspected
of a touch of senility.
Oh, that's ridiculous.
I should think the board would
You've been like a new man
since your vacation.
The board's as fair and all-knowing
as a hospital board can be.
Oh, I agree with you,
I'm as able and brilliant as ever.
But having crumbled once,
I might crumble again.
- You were overworked.
- A charming diagnosis
I shall always remember
your cheerfulness today...
as a lesson in how
to accept reality, Dr. Murchison.
Don't be too taken in
by my happy air, Constance.
It's the least difficult way
of saying good-bye to 20 years.
- Yes, l... I know. Come in.
- [Doorbell Buzzes]
Your mail, Dr. Petersen,
and Mr. Garmes.
Come in, Mr. Garmes.
You're not leaving today?
I'll see you again?
I shall hover around for a while
like an old mother hen.
At least until Dr. Edwardes
is firmly on the nest.
[Door Closes]
How do you feel today,
Mr. Garmes?
Somewhat better, Doctor. The thing
seems a little less troublesome.
May I do that for you, Doctor?
No, thank you. No, no.
I can do this myself very well.
Please sit down.
I'll be with you in a moment.
So that's the mighty
Anthony Edwardes.
He looks a little younger
than I expected.
He's only brought one suitcase. Perhaps
he doesn't intend to remain very long.
Leave those daydreams
to Dr. Murchison.
Gentlemen, our new chief,
Dr. Anthony Edwardes. Dr. Fleurot.
- How do you do?
- I am Dr. Graff.
- Dr. Hanish.
- How do you do?
There are still some staff
members missing, Dr. Edwardes.
These are your quarters.
They're very festive
for an institution.
Dr. Edwardes, Dr. Murchison.
How do you do, Dr. Murchison?
I've heard a great deal about you, sir.
And I, naturally, about you.
You're younger than I thought you'd be.
My age hasn't
caught up with me yet.
Mine has, it seems. I'm pleased to
hand over the reins to steadier hands.
I'm leaving you my library
which contains, amongst other
your latest volume,
The Labyrinth of the Guilt Complex.
An excellent work. I hope Green Manors
will inspire others as fine.
I'm very grateful.
I don't know the formal words
for an abdication, Dr. Edwardes.
May I say merely that these
quarters which I've occupied
Will you excuse me?
I spent a half hour
with Dr. Edwardes.
I must say, I was most
favorably impressed.
I intend to learn
a great deal from Dr. Edwardes.
I think we all can from a man
with such obvious talents.
- You're familiar with his work?
- Mm-hmm, yes. I've read all his books.
A very keen, unorthodox mind.
Well, it would be dreadful
if Dr. Murchison's successor
He's joining us.
I think you know everyone here,
Dr. Edwardes.
- No, not yet.
- Oh, this is Dr. Petersen.
- How do you do?
- Dr. Edwardes.
Dr. Hanish has been
showing me the grounds.
It's a remarkable
institution, Dr. Murchison.
It must be quite beautiful
in the summer.
I pointed out to Dr. Edwardes
our various open air diversions
Dr. Murchison always argued
we did not do enough in that
Let me warn you that Dr. Petersen
is a frustrated gymnast.
Well, Dr. Fleurot considers anything
beyond sitting and standing gymnastics.
I imagine you're
very fond of sports.
Yes, I am. And I miss them,
particularly winter sports.
- Did you show Dr. Edwardes
the elm grove?
Well, that's where we hope
to have our new swimming pool.
Oh, I'm a great believer
in the swimming pool.
There's a perfect spot
for it among the elms.
Not an oblong one,
but an irregular pool, something...
something like this.
You know?
The bathhouse, it should be here...
I take it that the supply of linen
at this institution is inexhaustible.
[Sighs]
Forgive me.
Oh, that reminds me of my
professor in psychiatry, Dr. Brulov.
He could never stand a sauce bottle
on the table, or even a salt shaker.
They took his appetite away.
I remember once
at a banquet in his honor...
he refused to sit
at the speaker's table...
because he was
completely surrounded by...
by ketchup.
Last night at dinner,
a dimple appeared at your cheek
and I detected the outcroppings of
a mother instinct toward Dr. Edwardes.
I detest that sort
of high school talk.
Your reactions have upset
one of my pet theories about you.
To wit, that you were immune
to psychoanalysts...
and would end up in the arms
of some Boob McNutt with spiked hair.
If I were looking for that type,
Dr. Fleurot, I would long ago
- [Doorbell Buzzes]
- Come in.
Hi... Oh, excuse me.
It's from Dr. Edwardes.
Ohhh, love notes already.
The French school of science.
I didn't want to come to this
institution, but my brother insisted.
I can see
no sense in it myself.
You see, I'm convinced I'm not
suffering from any hallucination...
but that my guilt is very real.
I know, Dr. Edwardes,
that I killed my father...
- and I'm willing
to pay the penalty for...
[Edwardes]
Come in.
Oh, thank you
for coming so soon.
I've been listening to Mr. Garmes
and thought you might help me out.
Oh, Mr. Garmes, you shouldn't
have disturbed Dr. Edwardes.
Oh, it's all right. I'm very
interested in Mr. Garmes' case.
Yes, I knew you would be.
He fits perfectly into your
Would you mind telling me
what you're talking about?
You're here to see if
we can cure your guilt complex
But I have no guilt complex.
I know what I know.
- I killed my father, and l...
- No, you didn't kill your father.
That's a misconception
that has taken hold of you.
Oh, I'm sorry, Doctor.
You were talking to him.
No, no. Go on.
People often feel guilty
over something they never did.
It usually goes back
to their childhood.
A child often wishes something
terrible would happen to someone.
And if something does
happen to that person...
the child believes
he has caused it.
And he grows up
with a guilt complex...
over a sin that was
only a child's bad dream.
What I am thinking
isn't true, then.
No. And in the course of analyzing
yourself, you will see that.
Would you care to go back
to your room, Mr. Garmes?
- [Door Opens]
- Harry.
I think we'd better put him
under drugs for a few days.
He looks agitated.
His conviction is curious.
But you've encountered such cases
very often, Dr. Edwardes.
You described them
perfectly in your book.
Yes. Yes, so I did.
- Uh, would you mind doing me a favor?
- Not at all, Doctor.
I have a headache, and I'd like to take
the afternoon off... with you.
I understand you're not
on duty till after dinner.
Well, I intended
typing up my notes...
Oh, please. I need a little fresh air,
and it might do you a bit of good.
I was going to lunch with Dr. Hanish.
He has an interesting kleptomaniac...
Oh, kleptomaniacs for lunch. They'll
steal the food right out of your mouth.
- [Phone Ringing]
- Excuse me.
Hello.
Yes, Dr. Edwardes.
What?
Yes, Anthony Edwardes.
Who? I'm sorry.
I don't get your name.
Norma Cramer.
Please, Miss Cramer,
I'm very busy and I don't know you.
Some girl claiming to be...
[Chuckles]
I hate practical jokes. Don't you?
People calling you up
and chirping, "Guess who I am."
Sounds like some
ex-patient of yours.
They are always full
of coy little tricks.
Very likely.
Come on, let's go.
We'll look at some sane trees, normal
grass and clouds without complexes.
[Laughs]
I think the greatest harm done the
human race has been done by the poets.
Oh, poets are dull boys, most of them,
but not especially fiendish.
They keep filling people's heads
with delusions about love...
writing about it as if
it were a symphony orchestra
Which it isn't, eh?
Of course not.
People fall in love, as they put it...
because they respond
to a certain hair coloring...
or vocal tones or mannerisms
that remind them of their parents.
- Sometimes for no reason at all.
- That's not the point.
The point is that people
read about love as one thing
Well, they expect kisses
to be like lyrical poems...
and embraces to be
like Shakespearean dramas.
And when they find out
differently...
then they get sick and
have to be analyzed, eh?
- Yes, very often.
- Professor, you're suffering
I beg your pardon!
[Laughs]
Here, can't get
through there like that.
Of course I can. Really.
I've been through here many times.
- Oh!
- Whoops. Hurt?
- No, not at all.
- Here.
No, I'm perfectly all right.
[Laughs]
Well, I usually
go on picnics here alone.
Oh, that doesn't
sound like much fun.
I haven't gone in for fun,
as you call it.
Oh, isn't this beautiful?
Perfect.
Oh, lunch, lunch.
What'll you have?
Ham or liverwurst, hmm?
Liverwurst.
Has anybody seen
our new chief today?
He has been tied up.
He frisked off
with Dr. Petersen at noon.
It's odd, spending his first day
running after Dr. Petersen
It'll do Constance good
to be drooled over.
Poor girl's withering away
with science.
I was telling her only recently
that something vital was missing
[Door Opens]
Oh, please don't get up.
I just came in because I learned
- Yes, I gave him a sedative.
- I'm very sorry I wasn't here.
- Constance, you look as if
you had an instructive time.
Gentlemen, notice her stocking.
The lady's been climbing trees.
Or lolling in a briar patch.
No, no, it's trees.
There are two leaves in her hair.
Allow me, Dr. Petersen.
You're surpassing yourself
as a charmer, Dr. Fleurot.
Don't run away.
Do have some coffee.
[Fleurot]
Oh, Dr. Petersen has already eaten...
as one can tell by the mustard
on her right forefinger.
I would say hot dogs
on the state highway.
Would you really? Your diagnosis
is, as usual, wrong, Dr. Fleurot.
Not hot dogs. Liverwurst. I'm very
sorry I have to leave this nursery.
- I must see Mr. Garmes.
- [Door Opens, Closes]
Looks as if we have Casanova himself
at the head of Green Manors.
Did you notice her blush every
time we mentioned his name?
It's very late.
L-I was going to read
your new book again.
I would like to discuss it.
I have never discussed
Of course, at school we had
several literary professors,
I sound rather nervous,
don't I?
Not at all.
I thought I wanted
to discuss your book with you.
I am amazed
at the subterfuge.
I don't want
to discuss it at all.
I understand.
It's quite remarkable to discover that
one isn't what one thought one was.
I mean, I've always been entirely
aware of what was in my mind.
And you're not now?
[Sighs]
Quite ridiculous.
It was stupid of me to come
in here like a distracted child.
- You're very lovely.
- Please don't talk that way.
You'll think I came in
to hear that.
- I know why you came in.
- Why?
Because something
has happened to us.
But it doesn't happen
like that, in a day.
It happens in a moment,
sometimes.
I felt it this afternoon.
It was like lightning striking.
It strikes rarely.
I don't understand
how it happened.
- What is it?
- It's not you.
It's something
about your robe.
My robe?
I don't understand.
Forgive me. L...
Something struck me.
I've been having a rather
bad time with my nerves lately.
Your robe...
I mean, the dark lines.
- You're ill.
- [Phone Ringing]
No, I'll be all right.
Hello.
Yes, Dr. Edwardes.
Yes. Yes. What?
Where is he?
I'll be there right away.
Mr. Garmes. He's run amuck.
He tried to murder Fleurot,
- Well, is it bad?
- I think so. He's in surgery.
I'll be right along.
He's lost a lot of blood,
but I think he'll pull through.
- What's the pulse?
- One hundred and forty.
It's going down.
Why are the lights out
in the corridor?
- What do you mean?
- It's dark.
That's why he did it!
'Cause the lights are out!
Put 'em on!
The doors.
Unlock them!
- You can't keep people in cells!
- Dr. Edwardes.
You fools, babbling
about guilt complexes.
What do you know about them?
He did it. He told me.
He killed his father.
[Panting]
Put the lights on, quick!
It's dark. It's dark.
- He's in collapse.
- He's ill.
- He didn't look like a heart case.
- Not heart, shock of some sort.
- We must get...
- Probably brought about by exhaustion.
Take him up to his room.
I'll take care of him.
I'm sorry.
I suppose I made
quite an exhibition of myself.
Who brought me down here?
You?
It's rather a mess.
Going to pieces in surgery.
Who are you?
I remember now.
Edwardes is dead.
I killed him
and took his place.
I'm someone else.
I don't know who.
I killed him. Edwardes.
I have no memory.
It's like looking into a mirror
and seeing nothing but the mirror.
And yet the image is there.
I know it's there.
I exist. I'm there.
How can a man lose
his memory, his name...
everything he's ever known
and still talk like this?
As if he were quite sane.
Are you afraid of me?
No. You're ill. Loss of memory
is not a difficult problem.
Yes, I know. Amnesia.
A trick of the mind
for remaining sane.
You remain sane by forgetting
something too horrible to remember.
You put the horrible thing
behind a closed door.
- We have to open that door.
- I know what's behind that door:
No. That's a delusion you
have acquired out of illness.
Will you answer me truthfully
and trust me?
I trust you, but it's no use.
I can't think.
I don't know who I am.
I don't know. I don't know.
- Who telephoned you yesterday?
- Telephoned me?
Yes, there in the office.
Yes, I remember.
What did she say?
She said that she was
my office assistant.
She was worried
about me, hadn't heard...
You mean, she was Dr. Edwardes'
assistant and hadn't heard from him?
What else did she say?
She didn't recognize my voice.
That I wasn't Dr. Edwardes.
- You hung up in anger?
- I was confused. My... My head ached.
- Was that your first doubt?
- First doubt?
The first time you became
confused as Edwardes?
Did anything else happen
before that?
Yes.
While I was in the hotel room
packing to come here...
I found a cigarette case
in my coat.
It frightened me.
I didn't know why it should.
Here.
The initials "J.B."
See them?
- Yes.
- When I saw them in the hotel room...
they made my head ache.
They're probably
your initials.
J.B. J.B.
You must sleep. I think when you wake
up, you'll be able to tell me more.
- If you trust me.
- I trust you.
It's late. You'd better
get some sleep yourself.
I'll be all right.
I'm-I'm sure there will be no
police inquiry for a few days...
and we'll talk about it and straighten
everything up before anything happens.
I'll come in in the morning and
report you're too ill for service.
[Door Closes]
I have been in Dr. Edwardes'
office for five years...
and the man who spoke to me
is not Dr. Edwardes.
He let me have my vacation
when he left on his.
I was very worried when I didn't
hear from him last week.
Then I thought he might have just
come here without reopening his office.
- That's why I telephoned.
- Show them the picture.
Oh, yes.
That's a different man.
He was taking a chance. Somebody might
have known what Edwardes looked like.
- You never saw the real Edwardes?
- No, I never met him.
But I felt something was wrong
from the moment our man appeared.
He didn't impress me
as a scientist.
And last night when he collapsed,
I became actually alarmed.
What do you think made him
break down last night?
It's obvious now... Garmes.
Our impostor, I'm almost certain,
is an amnesia case.
Garmes brought him back
to reality for an instant.
And being unable to face the truth
of who he was, he collapsed.
- You think he may have killed Edwardes?
- There's no question of it.
He killed Dr. Edwardes and took his
place in order to conceal his crime...
by pretending
the victim was still alive.
This sort of unrealistic act
is typical...
of the shortsighted cunning
that goes with paranoid behavior.
But we're wasting time, gentlemen.
His room is upstairs.
[Doorbell Buzzing]
[Buzzing Continues]
[Knocking]
Oh, uh, this is Dr. Petersen.
These gentlemen
are from the police...
The police?
What has happened?
Nothing to be alarmed about.
Our Dr. Edwardes turns out to be
and is very likely guilty
of having murdered the real Edwardes.
- He's disappeared.
- Oh. He is not in his room?
You left him
in his room, miss?
- Yes.
- Did he say anything?
About himself?
About why he broke down?
No. He was not himself.
He was unable to speak coherently.
You don't seem very surprised
to learn that this Dr. Edwardes...
is a fake
and may be guilty of murder.
L-I'm used to such surprises
in my work.
You suspected something, then?
No. I thought his collapse
due to a mental strain.
That's a funny diagnosis for a fellow
who's supposed to have just come
I made no medical diagnosis.
I was shocked to see him collapse,
We were all pretty shocked, Sheriff.
The fellow took us all in.
All except Dr. Murchison.
And he didn't say anything that might
give you an idea of where he went?
No.
He may be hanging around. We'll
have to go over the grounds first.
I'm sorry this has happened
to you, Constance.
I felt like warning you
about him, but I wasn't certain.
Don't worry.
It's not your fault.
They're bound to find him. I'll keep
you informed of the police activities.
I say the fellow expected
to get away with it, like any criminal.
Nonsense. Obviously
a case of amnesia.
He hadn't the faintest notion
of who he was or what he was doing.
What do you say, Constance?
I, I don't know.
You know, if you were anybody
but Constance Petersen...
the human glacier
and the custodian of truth...
- I'd say...
- Yes, you'd say what?
My dear, forgive me my scurvy thoughts.
You are telling the truth.
I was going to say that
you were holding something back.
I'm a sentimental ass.
A woman like you...
could never become involved emotionally
with any man, sane or insane.
I suggest you change
the subject, Fleurot.
I will be very interested
to ask him certain questions...
when they bring him back here,
no matter what you think.
- You'll never ask our
mystery man any questions.
For the very good reason
the police will never find him alive.
Amnesia case of that sort
with the police after him...
Fellow will put an end to his
pain, nightmare fantasies...
either by blowing his brains out
or dropping himself out of a window.
You're offending Dr. Petersen
with your callousness.
I'm sorry, Constance, that our
staff still retains the manners
Why, I'm not offended. I think
Dr. Fleurot's ideas are quite accurate.
But I'm rather tired.
Good night. Good night.
[Radio Newscaster]
The police have asked me to announce...
that our neighborhood roads
are free of the dangerous madman
The search for the impostor
has shifted to Manhattan.
This is WQZK, Rutland,
George Bell.
[Announcer] We now resume
our regularly scheduled program.
## [Big Band]
[Sighs]
Sure feels good to take
the weight off your feet.
I'm from Pittsburgh.
There's a town for you.
Really can meet people
in Pittsburgh.
Friendly.
A fellow could live and die in this
town, and he couldn't meet nobody.
How about you and me having
a nice little drink together
No, thank you. L...
You don't have to be
so snooty about it.
I'll have you know, madam, that I know
better people than you in Pittsburgh.
Yeah, I'm sure you're a great
social success, given half a chance.
Now you're talkin'.
Do you mind not sitting
in my lap in public?
That's enough of that.
Beat it.
I'll have you know I'm a guest in this
hotel. Who do you think you are?
I'm the house detective.
Get going.
Aw, this town's
gettin' worse and worse.
Oh, that's all right, lady.
You don't have to go.
I'm sorry
you were being annoyed.
I've been watching you, and I figured
something like this might happen.
See, the chief duty
of a house detective...
is to spot trouble in advance.
- You're not registered here, are you?
- No.
Well, I didn't think so,
the way you were wandering around.
Lookin' for somebody, huh?
Oh, now, don't be afraid of me.
I, uh, I've got you spotted
as a lady in trouble...
and from out of town.
Schoolteacher
or, uh, librarian.
- Which is it?
- Schoolteacher.
I thought so. They always look
like they just lost something.
- Maybe I can help you.
- I don't think so. Thank you.
Looking for some man, I suppose.
Must be a relative.
And from the worried look,
I'd say a pretty close one.
A husband, for instance.
Oh, I'm really amazed.
- I hit it, huh?
- But how could you tell?
Well, I'm a kind of a psychologist.
You know, you gotta be in my line.
Now would you mind filling in
a few of the blank spaces for me?
Oh, no.
It's just that we quarreled.
Oh, and then you got sorry
and you came running after him?
That's the usual psychology.
But now you're afraid to face him.
Oh, no, no.
It's that l...
I don't know what room he's in.
He told a friend
he was coming to this hotel...
but under a different name
so I couldn't find him.
But I must find him and apologize
and make him feel better.
When did he arrive here?
Yesterday morning.
Give me a description of him.
He's-He's very tall
and, and attractive.
Uh, dark hair,
a rather rugged face...
and brown eyes and one suitcase.
I'll go check on him.
[Sighs]
- Did you find him?
- Well, I think we got a line.
About 25 guys answering your
description registered here yesterday.
These are their
registration cards.
I figured you might
recognize the handwriting.
That's very clever of you.
This is his handwriting.
John Brown, huh?
Not much imagination for an alias.
- Room 3033.
- Oh, thank you very much.
- I was going to sit here
all day watching for him.
I'm glad to be of service.
I'm a married man myself...
and I know how it feels to have a wife
come chasing after you to apologize.
[Doorbell Buzzes]
Constance.
What did you come for?
You don't owe me anything.
I'm going to do
what I want to do.
Take care of you and cure you
and remain with you till that happens.
But you can't.
You can't help hide a criminal.
You're not going to jeopardize
your standing as a doctor.
You're just getting started.
I won't let you be stupid about it.
I couldn't bear it away from you.
I went through yesterday holding
my breath as if I were being hunted.
I couldn't eat or work
or do anything but think of you.
So I had to come.
I'll get a room on this floor.
I'm here as your doctor only.
It has nothing to do with love.
Nothing at all.
Try remembering.
Let your mind go back
to your childhood.
Was it happy?
Whom did you know in your childhood?
I'm haunted, but l...
I can't see by what.
- It's no use.
- You lived somewhere.
You had a mother.
You were loved. You had friends.
Yes. Probably a wife.
Can you remember her?
Oh, I didn't say I had one.
I said I probably had.
No, darling. Thank heaven
I can't remember a wife.
I would like to ask you
a medical question.
Constance, would you mind
not prodding me?
It mixes me up. L...
I can't remember anything...
except that I love you.
How would you diagnose a pain
in the right upper quadrant?
A pain that is persistent.
Oh, a gall bladder, possibly
a heart case or pneumonia...
- depending on the patient's history.
- It's obvious you're a doctor.
Yes. The eminent Dr. X.
And if we can unlock
one tiny memory...
it'll give us a key
to the others.
No.
The only thing
that comes to my mind...
that I keep thinking over and over,
is the logic of the situation.
- What logic?
- That it was I who was with Edwardes.
"Police believe the impostor
who escaped from Green Manors...
to be the patient who visited
the real Dr. Edwardes...
in the Cumberland Mountains the day
that the noted psychiatrist disappeared.
No trace of Dr. Edwardes
has been found...
since he left the Cumberland resort
in the company of his supposed patient."
- Do you remember that?
- No.
Then why do you believe
that you were with him?
Because wherever we went,
I came back with his identity.
I wouldn't have come back
as Dr. Edwardes if I hadn't
How would I have known
he was dead if I hadn't been
- Were you?
- I, I don't remember, but...
logically I know
that I must have been.
And logically I also know
why the body hasn't been found.
Because it was hidden by me.
Don't you see that
you're imagining all this?
You call yourself names. You insist
without proof that you're a murderer.
You know what that is,
don't you?
Whoever you are, it's a guilt complex
that speaks for you.
A guilt fantasy that goes
way back to your childhood.
I think you're quite mad.
You're much crazier than I.
Do all this for a creature
without a name.
To run off
with a pair of initials.
The police have not given your name
or case history to the papers.
That must mean only one thing...
that your name was not
in Dr. Edwardes' files.
You were in an accident.
Where was it?
What happened to your hand?
Your hand was burned.
You've had an operation
in the last six months.
And skin grafts.
Third-degree burns.
Your hand was burned.
Where?
- It hurts.
- Try remembering.
[Panting]
My hand hurts.
Your hand is remembering.
Open your mind, and the pain will leave.
- Where did it happen?
- I can't. It hurts.
- What happened?
- It's burning. My hand's burning.
Try to remember.
Oh, my dear,
are you all right?
I'm all right.
What happened?
You relived an accident
you've been in.
But the memory only touched
the part of your mind that feels.
But it's a beginning.
It really is.
- You'll feel better soon.
- [Doorbell Buzzes]
- Who could that be?
- Oh, I know.
I sent out for the later
editions of the papers.
- You ordered the afternoon
papers, didn't you?
- They just came.
I brought them right up.
- Here you are. Thank you.
- Oh, thanks.
My picture's in the paper.
He recognized me.
We've got to go, quick.
We can't pack.
Listen.
When you left the mountains,
you must have passed through New York.
Wherever you came from,
wherever you went, you must
You must have heard Edwardes
ask for tickets to somewhere.
I don't remember.
You will. When you come
to the ticket window...
try to relive that
other time with Edwardes.
Try to repeat
what was said then.
Ask for the same tickets.
I'll try.
One. Philadelphia.
[Ticket Agent] Philadelphia. $3.39,
including the federal tax. Thank you.
Washington, one way.
You went someplace with Edwardes.
Ask for tickets
to that same place.
[Ticket Agent]
$8.46, including tax.
Thank you.
What is it?
What do you want, sir?
Well, please step aside.
- I want two tickets.
- Where to?
- Rome. Rome.
- To where?
- Rome.
- What Rome?
He means Rome, Georgia.
Is anything wrong?
My husband is ill.
I'm taking him home.
Here you are.
Two tickets to Rome, Georgia.
He'll be all right in a minute.
These dizzy spells go away quickly.
- He looks pretty sick.
I'll call a doctor.
Do you feel better now,
darling? Darling?
Pull yourself together.
You're all right.
When does the train
for Rome leave?
The Birmingham Special
leaves in ten minutes, track 17.
- I feel better now.
- Thank you.
That's all right, lady. I'll take you
to the train in case anything happens.
Oh, he has recovered now.
You're very nice to offer help,
Act as if we are taking this train.
We'll walk down a ways
What's the matter
with this train?
The policeman heard us
buying the tickets.
- Did he act suspicious?
- No, he was very nice.
But when he goes to the police
station tonight, he may find
They'll telegraph Rome, Georgia,
and have us picked up.
We can't go back to the hotel. They'll
have a million police there by now.
We're not going back.
We're going to Rochester.
Come on. We'll go
over to Grand Central Station.
Oh, by the way, what are we
going to Rochester for?
Oh, we're going
to visit Dr. Brulov.
Oh, that's the fellow
who doesn't like sauce bottles.
- He was my analyst.
He psychoanalyzed me.
Oh, all analysts have to be
psychoanalyzed by other analysts
Ah, that's to make sure
that they're not too crazy.
Apparently the mind is never too ill
to make jokes about psychoanalysis.
- I'm sorry. I'm a pig.
- No, I am. I keep forgetting
So do I. When I hold you
like this, I feel entirely well.
Will you love me just as much
when I'm normal?
Oh, I'll be insane about you.
[Laughing]
I am normal.
At least there's nothing
wrong with me...
that a nice long kiss
wouldn't cure.
Oh, I have never treated
a guilt complex that way before.
- We don't want to attract attention.
- Everybody's doing it.
[Laughs]
- You're both going?
- Yes. Y-Yes.
Oh, don't read the paper.
Let's pick up where we left off.
- Pick up what?
- Try to recall the first moment
- Darling, I have
a confession to make.
As a doctor,
you irritate me.
I sit here swooning with love,
and then suddenly...
you ask me a question
and I don't like you anymore.
Do you have to sit there
smiling at me like some smug,
I can't help smiling.
That's what happens in analysis.
As the doctor begins
to uncover the truth in a patient...
said patient develops a fine,
hearty hatred of said doctor.
Well, you're going to hate me
a great deal before we're through.
- And you're going to like that?
- As a scientist, yes.
And if I should happen to biff you one,
you'll consider that a sort of diploma?
Yes, but don't biff too hard.
You know, I think we should go on
with our investigation.
- We have some new facts
to work with now.
You're a doctor,
you were in an accident...
your hand and forearm
were burned...
- and you were in Rome.
- I was never in Rome in my life.
You were either there
or going there.
You remembered something no doubt
connected with the burning of your hand.
Rome. Think of Rome.
Maybe Rome, Italy.
When did you go to Rome?
What did you do in Rome?
Think.
[Mutters]
Yes, I remember. I remember something.
A fighter plane spotted us.
- You were flying?
- Transport, Medical Corps,
- What happened?
- They hit us. Caught fire.
What else?
I don't know.
L-l-It blacks out.
You left the army?
Yeah. I probably deserted it.
I hated it.
I hated killing.
I can remember that much.
Your guilt fantasies were obviously
inflamed by your duties as a soldier.
Oh, stop it.
Babbling like some phony
King Solomon.
You sit there full of half-witted
double-talk that doesn't make sense.
If there's anything I hate,
it's a smug woman.
Darling, we're just beginning.
Don't biff too hard yet.
I worked as Dr. Brulov's assistant
for a year, right after my internship.
He got me the post at Green Manors.
You'll like Alex.
I doubt that. One psychoanalyst
in my hair is enough.
- What are you gonna tell him?
- That we are on our honeymoon.
Oh, Doctor, you think of
the most wonderful descriptions.
Good evening.
Is Dr. Brulov in?
No, he went out right after dinner.
He ought to be back soon.
Would you mind telling him
I've left his supper on the table?
I'm sorry,
but I can't wait any longer.
Oh, and there are two gentlemen
waiting for him in there.
- How do you do?
- [Man] How do you do?
How do you do?
How's your mother been lately?
Oh, she's still complaining
about rheumatism.
She figures I ought to get
transferred down to Florida.
I said, "Do you expect me to sacrifice
all chance of promotion...
just because
you've got rheumatism?"
Did you take the subject up
with Hennessy?
Yeah. He said a transfer
could be arranged...
but I'd probably have to start
all over again as a sergeant.
I said, "Personally,
I think that's unfair...
after all the work I did
in that narcotics case. "
- And what did Hennessy say to that?
- Oh, a lot of things.
He made some crack about me
being a mama's boy.
[Ringing]
[Ringing Continues]
Oh, pardon me.
That may be for me.
I gave Headquarters this number.
Hello.
Yes, this is Lieutenant Cooley.
Any new developments?
Well, when
did you find that out?
No. Right. I'll be down later.
Good-bye.
[Door Opens]
- Alex!
- [Brulov] Who is it, please?
- Oh, my old friend!
- Alex!
- My dear darling!
- Oh, l-I didn't have time
- I just arrived.
- Imagine I find you here.
Oh, I would have
come home quicker.
I was giving a lecture
at the army hospital.
- Are these gentlemen with you?
- No, I'm here with...
Dr. Brulov, I'm Lieutenant Cooley
of Central Station.
- This is Sergeant Gillespie.
- What for?
We thought you might give us
some data on Dr. Edwardes.
Data? What is this kind
of persecution?
I told the policeman yesterday
I know nothing about Edwardes.
But yesterday
you had some kind of theory.
[Brulov]
I explained to the policeman...
that if Edwardes took along with him
on vacation a paranoid patient...
he was a bigger fool
than I ever knew he was.
It is the same
as playing with a loaded gun.
[Cooley] Do you think this
patient might have killed him?
I'm not thinking anything.
I am not a bloodhound.
Was Dr. Edwardes
a great friend of yours?
What are you talking about?
The man was impossible.
You had a quarrel with him when you
went back in New York, I understand.
Not New York. In Boston,
at the psychiatry convention.
What kind of an analyst is it
who wants to cure psychosis...
by taking people skating
or to a bowling alley?
I understand you threatened
to punch his nose.
All I did
was get up and walk out...
and kick over a few chairs
which nobody was sitting in.
So you don't have to ask me any more
questions. You have now the facts.
Well, thank you very much.
I'm sorry to have bothered you.
If anything turns up,
we'll let you know.
- Good-bye, ma'am. Good night, sir.
- Good night.
[Door Opens, Closes]
What do you suppose they
are snooping around me for?
The next they will give me
is the third degree.
I am so glad to see you. I was going to
write you, but it happened so suddenly.
- I got married.
- Uh, who is married?
Oh, Alex.
My husband, John Brown.
- I'm glad to meet you, officially.
- Oh, so you are married!
Oh, there is nothing so nice
as a new marriage.
No psychosis yet, no regressions,
no guilt complexes.
I congratulate you...
and wish you have babies
and not phobias.
How about we have a glass
of beer like in the old days?
Yes. The truth is
that we have no hotel room.
- All the hotels were so crowded.
- What do you want with a hotel?
That's for millionaires,
not lovebirds on a honeymoon.
You will stay right here.
Look how I'm living by myself
with a can opener.
My housekeeper is gone to war.
My secretary is a WAC.
And I got a cleaning woman
who can't cook and who hates me.
Cook me my coffee in the morning
and the house is yours.
- That's wonderful of you, Alex.
- Ah, there is nothing
It's nice to see
my old assistant...
the youngest
but the best one I ever had.
But who knows now?
As my old friend Zannenbaum
used to say...
"Women make
the best psychoanalysts...
till they fall in love.
After that,
they make the best patients."
[Chuckling]
Good night and happy dreams...
which we will analyze
at breakfast.
Good night, Dr. Brulov,
and thanks for everything.
Any husband of Constance is
a husband of mine, so to speak.
- Good night, Alex.
- Good night.
- You were superb with the police.
- Was I?
Oh, carried it off
like a grade-A gun moll.
Well, I felt terribly stupid for a few
minutes, but it turned out very well.
Providing the professor
isn't wiser than he seems.
Alex? Oh, no.
Things are a little different.
No, Alex didn't think anything.
He's sweet.
He may be sweet, but he didn't
even ask us where our bags were.
Alex is always like that...
in a complete dream state, socially.
Do you know,
this room does look changed.
But it isn't.
It's I who am changed.
It's called transfer of affects.
- What is?
- The fact that everything seems
Oh. That's what it's called,
is it?
- Did the police disturb you?
- Oh, no.
One ignores such trifles
on a honeymoon.
I take it
this is your first honeymoon.
Yes. I mean...
it would be if it were...
For what it's worth, I...
I can't remember ever having
kissed any other woman before.
I have nothing to remember
of that, that nature either.
Oh, you're very sweet.
- Of course, I'm no child.
- Oh, far from it.
I'm well aware that we're all
bundles of inhibitions.
Oh, dynamite dumps.
No.
- Oh, please don't do that.
- Why?
It isn't ethical.
I'm here as your doctor.
Well, you can stop worrying, Doctor.
I'm gonna sleep on the couch.
No, that's also unethical.
This honeymoon is complicated
enough without your dragging
- I suppose the floor is out.
- The patient always sleeps in the bed.
And the doctor occupies
the couch, fully dressed.
Oh, I see you know the rules.
- You remember something.
- No.
- This room reminds you of something.
You're resisting a memory.
What is in your mind?
- I don't know.
- Yes you do! You're resisting it!
Don't start that again! Don't stand
there with that wiseacre look.
- I'm sick of your double-talk.
- You were looking at the bed.
What frightens you?
White lines.
When I made fork marks
on the tablecloth, they agitated you.
That night you kissed me,
you pushed me away because of my robe.
It was white.
It had dark lines on it.
Why does the color white frighten you?
Why do lines frighten you?
- Think of white! White.
- 'Cause it frightens me. I can't look.
Don't run away! Stand still!
Look at the white spread!
Darling.
Oh, darling.
You mustn't be frightened.
No, you mustn't.
We are making progress.
We have the word white
on our side.
Is that you, Mr. Brown?
Oh, I thought it was you.
I was unable to sleep,
so I came down to work.
When you're old,
you don't need to sleep so much.
I'm just having a glass of milk
and some crackers.
Join me, please.
I'll get another glass.
I'm glad to have company.
Nobody likes to have crackers
and milk by himself.
When I was a young man,
I was always saying...
"Ah, if I could only
get along by myself...
instead of wasting my time
with people...
I would be happy. "
Now I am saying just the opposite.
This is the secret of old age.
Everything becomes
just the opposite.
Do you know who makes
the most trouble in the world?
Old people.
They are always worrying what is
going to be in the world tomorrow...
after they are gone.
That's why they have wars...
because old people got nothing
else they can get excited about.
Well... we will drink to you.
To when we're young and know
nothing except living.
Alex!
Alex, are you all right?
- Oh.
- [Sighs]
Good morning.
Yes, I am all right. Thank you.
- Oh, I fell asleep in the chair.
- Yes.
- What time is it?
- 7:00.
I was dreaming this morning
I get some real coffee.
Yes. M-My husband must have gone out
very early this morning.
- You didn't happen...
- He didn't go out.
He's over there on the couch.
He's all right.
He's sleeping fine.
My dear child,
do you think old Alex Brulov...
one of the biggest brains
who is in psychiatry...
is unable to make out
two and two come out four?
[Sighs]
I should have known.
The moment I see you with a husband
whose pupils are enlarged...
who has a tremor
of the left hand...
who is on a honeymoon
with no baggage...
and whose name is John Brown...
I know practically
what is going on.
What happened?
Only what I expected.
There is no use taking chances
with a possibly dangerous case.
I sit here waiting.
If you scream, I'm ready.
So he comes downstairs,
and he's dangerous.
I can see by his face.
So I keep talking while I put
some bromide into a glass of milk...
enough to knock out three horses.
When he falls down,
I run up to see you...
you are sleeping like a baby...
and I come back here to watch out.
Well, the struggle against
his condition agitates him at times...
but there is no danger in him.
This is what I found
in his hand last night.
He didn't know he had that.
Alex, you mustn't think that.
He didn't try to do anything
to you. He couldn't.
My dear child,
he's not responsible.
But that's not correct.
I'm just a little more experienced
with this type than you.
I grant you know infinitely more
than I do, but in this ca...
Do not complete this sentence with
the usual female contradictions!
You grant me
I know more than you...
but on the other hand
you know more than me.
- Women's talk. Bah!
- Alex, what are you going to do?
- Something more for you than for me.
- Alex.
- I'm calling the police.
- No, no, please!
You are giving me orders.
My own pupil.
You don't know this man.
You know only science.
You know his mind,
but you don't know his heart.
We are speaking
of a schizophrenic...
and not a Valentine.
We are speaking of a man.
[Chuckling]
Oh. Oh, I see. Love.
Look at you. Dr. Petersen...
the promising psychoanalyst,
is now all of a sudden a schoolgirl...
in love with an act,
nothing else.
Alex, let me tell you about him.
What is there for you to say?
We both know that the mind
of a woman in love...
is operating on the lowest level
of the intellect.
The doctor told me not to smoke
in the morning, but I am too excited.
Oh, you are right.
I'm not an analyst,
not even a doctor here.
I'm not talking to you as one.
But believe me...
not what I say, but what I feel.
The mind isn't everything.
The heart
can see deeper sometimes.
A police investigation might
ruin his chances for recovery,
My dear, he killed Dr. Edwardes.
How can you help him?
He didn't. He didn't.
But if it turns out he did,
which I'm good and certain it will...
It won't. You yourself taught
me what Freud says...
"A man cannot do anything
in amnesia that his real
And how do you know
what his real character is?
I know. I know.
She knows.
This is the way
science goes backward.
Who told you what he is?
Freud... or a crystal ball?
I couldn't feel this way
toward a man who was bad...
or had committed murder.
I couldn't feel this pain
for someone who was evil.
You are 20 times crazier than him.
[Mockingly]
She couldn't love him if he was no good.
This is baby talk, nothing else.
What do you want I should do?
Give me time to treat him
and cure him...
before the police find him and shock
him into an incurable condition.
- This could take a year.
- Oh, no, no.
Or a half a year.
We should sit and hide
for a half a year...
waiting to find out if he's
going to cut your throat...
my throat and...
and set fire to the house.
Oh, my dear girl.
Even to a woman in love...
such a situation must seem
a little unreasonable.
Just a few more days, Alex,
before you turn him over.
Just a few more days.
And then if I can't do anything...
if we both can't,
well, then you call the police.
You're not hiding a criminal.
There is no evidence against him
He's wanted only as a possible witness
as to what happened to Dr. Edwardes.
Well, in his present condition,
he could tell the police nothing.
Don't you see you are doing
nothing against the law?
We are helping them by investigating
the patient as doctors...
doctors who want the truth
even more than they do.
- All right.
- You'll wait?
Go make me coffee.
I'll pretend to myself I'm
acting sensible for a few days.
[Crying]
Oh, Alex.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
It's, uh... I'll make you coffee...
with an egg in it.
- Who are you?
- I'm Dr. Brulov.
Brulov.
Oh, yeah, that's right.
[Sighs] Bromides?
Who's been feeding me bromides?
I gave you... to sleep.
Brulov.
Oh, yes. Rochester.
- What's your name?
- [Sighs]
I don't know.
- Constance told you.
- Oh, nobody told me.
If I don't know a patient with amnesia
when I see one, what do I know?
- You don't remember
your father or mother?
- Wife or sweetheart?
- No!
Don't fight me.
I'm going to help you, if I can.
I'm going to be
your father image.
I want you to look on me
like your father.
Trust me, lean on me.
This is a shortcut,
but we haven't much time.
All right.
Go ahead. I'm leaning.
Maybe you've got something
you want to tell me...
a single thought, a few words
in the corner of your head?
Go on. Talk to me.
Whatever comes into your head,
just say what it is.
- There's nothing.
- Maybe you dreamt something.
- Yeah.
- What did you dream?
I don't believe in dreams.
That Freud stuff's a lot of hooey.
Hooey?
You are a fine one to talk.
You've got amnesia,
and you've got a guilt complex.
You don't know if you're coming
or going from someplace.
But Freud is hooey.
This you know.
[Scoffs]
Wise guy.
[Sighing]
You don't like me, Papa.
You want I should help you...
or not?
[Chuckles]
I'm sorry.
I'll explain to you
about dreams...
so you don't think it is hooey.
The secrets of who you are and what
has made you run away from yourself...
all these secrets
are buried in your brain...
but you don't want
to look at them.
The human being very often doesn't
want to know the truth about himself...
because he thinks
it will make him sick.
So he makes himself sicker,
trying to forget.
- Do you follow this?
- Yeah.
- Oh, how do you feel?
- Ah, coffee.
Awful.
The patient is going to tell us
what he dreamt.
Oh, fine. I'll take notes.
I'll get my glasses.
Now, here's where dreams
come in.
They tell you
what you are trying to hide...
but they tell it to you
all mixed up...
like pieces of a puzzle
that don't fit.
The problem
of the analyst is...
to examine this puzzle...
and put the pieces together
in the right place...
and find out what the devil you
are trying to say to yourself.
Let's see.
I kept thinking while I was dreaming
that all this meant something...
that there was some other meaning
in it that I ought to find out.
We'll find out.
I can't make out just
what sort of a place it was.
It seemed to be a gambling house.
But there weren't any walls, just a lot
of curtains with eyes painted on them.
A man was walking around
with a large pair of scissors
And then a girl came in
with hardly anything on...
and started walking around
the gambling room kissing everybody.
She came to my table first.
[Brulov]
Did you recognize this kissing bug?
Well, I'm afraid she looked
a little like Constance.
Uh-huh. This is plain,
ordinary, wishful dreaming.
- Go on.
- [Chuckles] Well...
I was sitting there playing cards
with a man who had a beard.
I was dealing to him.
I turned up the seven of clubs.
He said,
"That makes 21. I win."
When he turned up his cards,
they were blank.
Just then the proprietor came in
and accused him of cheating.
The proprietor yelled,
"This is my place and if I catch you
I'm sorry
about that kissing bit.
I'm glad you didn't dream of me as
an eggbeater as one of my patients did.
- Why? What would that mean?
- Never mind.
Well, does it make any sense
to you what I dreamed?
Not yet. You are trying
to tell yourself something.
What it is
we'll figure out later.
There's a lot more to it.
Go on and try
to recall the details.
The more cockeyed the better
for the scientific side of it.
He was leaning over the sloping
roof of a high building.
It was the man with the beard.
I yelled at him to watch out.
But then he went over, slowly,
with his feet in the air.
And then I saw the proprietor
again... the man in the mask.
He was hiding behind a tall chimney
and he had a small wheel in his hand.
I saw him drop the wheel
on the roof.
Suddenly I was running. Then I heard
something beating over my head.
It was a great pair of wings.
The wings chased me...
and almost caught up with me
when I came to the bottom of the hill.
[Chuckles] I must have escaped.
I don't remember.
That's all there was.
I woke up and saw Dr. Brulov.
- Have some coffee.
- Thanks.
- Something's happening.
- What is it?
- Snow.
- The light frightened him.
Photophobia.
No, it was the snow.
That's the white he's afraid of.
Snow and those tracks.
- What tracks?
- The sled tracks in the snow.
The first symptom he revealed
was shock at the sight of fork
And my robe.
It had dark lines on it.
And last night,
the white coverlet...
like those dark tracks
in the snow.
We'll pull the blinds down,
please.
Dr. Edwardes was fond of sports.
He mentions tennis and skiing
in his book as valuable...
in the treatment
of mental disorders.
Skiing.
Ski tracks in the snow.
That's what those dark lines
symbolized for him.
His horror at them means that
they are immediately connected
Yes, a murder on skis.
Where did Edwardes go for his skiing?
We must find out.
Can you tell us where? Try.
He has told us of it,
in his dream.
Let me see your notes.
What can we do for him?
Oh, you're not his mama.
You're an analyst.
Leave him alone.
He will come out of this by himself.
The sloping roof.
That means only a mountainside.
And they were skiing.
And the father image...
the bearded man... is Dr. Edwardes.
That's very simple. Dr. Edwardes
plunged over the precipice while skiing.
And then a shadow chases him
up and down a hill.
That could mean he was escaping
from a valley.
Skiing resorts are often called
valleys, like, like Sun Valley.
He was being pursued by a winged
figure... a witch or a harpy.
No, the figure was you.
If you grew wings,
you would be an angel.
The dream's trying to tell him
the name of the resort.
Angel. Angel Valley.
Do you remember Angel Valley?
- No.
- We could call a travel agency
It wasn't Angel Valley.
I remember it.
It was a place...
called Gabriel Valley.
What else do you remember now?
Who was the masked figure
in your dream?
It was an accident. Do you remember
that? A skiing accident.
- Dr. Edwardes went over a snow cliff.
- It was no accident!
I can't stand this anymore!
I've had enough of it.
No, we have to go
to Gabriel Valley.
You've got to go with me.
This is for Cooley
when he comes in.
I'll tell him.
[Constance]
At 4:45? Thank you. Good-bye.
[Hangs Up Phone]
There's a train leaving
in an hour.
- We can make connections
for Gabriel Valley.
I can't go on endangering you.
- I know about last night.
- Nothing happened.
But it will. I've got to end it
before it does.
I love you,
but I'm not worth loving.
Darling,
you can help me afterward.
There's no help afterward.
If you give yourself up
there is no afterwards
for either of us.
- I can cure you.
- But you can't undo a murder.
- There is none to undo.
- I killed him.
- Oh, stop.
- And now you. Last night, I mean.
Don't try to stop me.
I've got to go.
Guilt, guilt. You've lived with it
for a long time, haven't you?
- Yes.
- Since childhood.
- What?
- Ever since childhood, you've
You've always felt guilty about
anything that happened around you.
What was it in your youth?
It must have been terrible...
for you to prefer to think
you murdered Edwardes rather
- Enough!
- You said you love me.
Look at me then.
Why am I fighting for you?
- Because I love you.
Because I need you.
- I want you to come with me
to Gabriel Valley.
When you see the hill where the accident
happened, you will remember it.
- We'll go skiing together
as you did with Edwardes.
You'll see your innocence.
You'll see what really happened.
You mean,
because it will happen again.
- Yes.
- And what if I killed him?
[Stair Creaks]
Isn't it true that
if the episode's repeated...
I'm likely to do the same
thing I did before?
Then how do you know
I won't kill again?
Because I'm convinced you didn't
kill in the first place.
You believe in me enough
to take such a chance?
Of course I do.
We are going back to that ski run.
We'll find out
what it was in your childhood
And we'll also find out
what happened to Dr. Edwardes.
You ever see her before?
Let's go.
I've always loved very feminine clothes
but never quite dared to wear them.
But I'm going to, after this.
I'm going to wear exactly
and you.
Even very, very funny hats.
You know, the kind that
make you look a little drunk.
[Train Whistle Blowing]
Put them on.
[J.B. 's Voice]
It was something in my childhood.
Something in my childhood!
I remember now!
I killed my brother!
I didn't kill my brother. It was
an accident. It was an accident!
That's what has haunted you all
your life. That was the memory
It's like looking into
a picture book... an old one.
Seeing the familiar pictures,
one at a time.
I went to Columbia Medical School.
I had a girl with a giggle who,
luckily, married my roommate Ken.
Oh, and by the way,
my name's John Ballyntine.
Oh, I'm very pleased
to meet you.
Another thing.
My, my army record's all right.
I was invalided out.
I ran into Dr. Edwardes when
I was in the Cumberland Mountains...
trying to recover
from some kind of nerve shock
He was on vacation,
but I asked him to help me.
And he invited me
to go skiing with him.
We went through New York, and I seem
to remember going to lunch somewhere.
I'm still a little bit vague
about that lunch part.
Then we arrived here, and
the accident happened at that spot.
Where you saved me.
Now, let's not have any
confusion about who saved whom.
Yes, he went over there,
all right.
It's still a little foggy,
but I do know...
that Edwardes was about 50 feet
ahead of me when he went over.
- I saw him plunge.
- That was the thing that set you off...
that stirred up
your old guilt complex...
and made you think
that you'd killed him.
So you had to run away from that
too, and you took on the role
to prove to yourself
that he wasn't dead.
So, therefore,
you had not killed him.
Professor, I never quite realized
in my amnesic state how lovely you are.
Oh, now that you got your head back,
you mustn't lose it again.
Oh, no. It's too late.
I'm beyond cure.
How does it feel
to be a great analyst?
- Oh, not so bad.
- And a great detective.
- Wonderful.
- And madly adored?
Very wonderful.
You'll look wonderful...
in white...
with a little orange blossom
in your hair.
That, that sounds vaguely as if it
has something to do with marriage.
That's a brilliant analysis,
Doctor.
- Oh.
- [Door Opens]
[J.B.]
Oh, hello.
You know Lieutenant Cooley
and Sergeant Gillespie from Rochester.
Yes, yes.
We know them quite well.
- How did you find us?
- Well, no thanks
We made a few inquiries
at the railroad station.
- You left a trail a mile wide.
- Well, you arrived
I believe
that's the usual expression.
We found the body of Dr. Edwardes.
It's almost exactly...
where you told the local police
it would be.
You remembered the spot
very well.
- Well, thank goodness
it's all cleared up.
I'm afraid a bullet was found
in the body.
T-T-That's impossible.
- It was in his back.
- The case is one of murder.
We shall have to detain you, sir.
It's my duty to inform you that anything
you say may be used against you.
No. No, you mustn't say
you killed him, darling.
Try to remember what happened
before Edwardes went over.
But when he said he killed him,
he wasn't himself.
He was in a state
of great mental distress.
But you can't put him away.
You can't!
It'll destroy his mind!
Don't you understand?
Good-bye, my dear.
We won't give up hope. I'm going
to fight and fight and get you free.
My dear girl, you cannot keep
bumping your head against reality...
and saying it is not there.
The evidence was definite.
We can't remove it
by wishing or crying.
He trusted me.
I led him into a trap.
I convicted him.
Is that real enough for you?
There is no one to blame.
The case was a little deeper
than you figured.
This often happens.
You must realize now one thing.
It is over for both of you.
It's not over.
- You will have other cases.
- It's not over. It never will be!
Don't ask me to stop.
I can't! I can't. [Sobbing]
Oh, I'm, I'm sorry.
I, l...
Thanks for straightening things out
with Dr. Murchison and everyone.
It is very sad...
to love and lose somebody.
But in a while, you will forget...
and you will take up
the threads of your life...
where you left off not so long ago.
And you will work hard.
There is lots of happiness
in working hard.
Maybe the most.
I will write to you.
Oh, Alex, you're very good.
- Very good.
- [Knock At Door]
I'm sorry to hurry you, Dr. Brulov,
but your car is waiting.
- You have just time.
- Oh, thank you.
I'm always late,
always forgetting.
A brilliant man.
I should have gone
to the station with him.
You're too tired. I know that
feeling of exhaustion only too well.
One must humor it,
or it explodes.
I shall try to help you,
in every way.
- You will take care of yourself?
- Yes.
And try to forget things
better forgotten.
You've got a great career
ahead of you, Constance.
Thank you. Well, at least
one good thing came out of all this.
You are back at Green Manors.
Who knows what would have happened
to the place under Dr. Edwardes?
I knew Edwardes only slightly.
I never really liked him.
But he was a good man,
in a way, I suppose.
Well, good night, Constance.
I hope you feel rested
in the morning.
[Murchison's Voice]
I knew Edwardes only slightly.
I never liked him very well.
I knew Edwardes slightly.
Knew Edwardes.
Knew Edwardes slightly.
Knew.
Come in.
I want to talk to you,
Dr. Murchison.
It's rather late.
I do need rest, Constance.
I must talk to you.
Nocturnal conferences
are bad for the nerves.
- Is it something about your work?
- Yes.
- Can't it wait till morning?
- It can't wait.
Well, do sit down.
Now, what's your problem?
It is a dream
one of my patients reported.
May I ask who the patient is?
The patient is John Ballyntine.
I fancied that.
And you're still working
on the possibility of his innocence.
Charming loyalty...
one of your most attractive
characteristics, Constance.
[Sighs]
What did he dream?
He dreamt
he was in a gambling house.
It was full of odd people
playing with blank cards.
Blank cards.
Obviously, the patient was trying
to deny it was a gambling house...
by dreaming of spurious cards.
One of the people in the place
went around cutting the drapes in half.
Another was a scantily dressed
girl who was kissing everybody.
With a little effort, one could almost
imagine them inmates of Green Manors.
That's what I had in mind,
Dr. Murchison.
Interesting notion
to play around with, isn't it?
Do go on.
There were eyes painted
on the curtains around the walls.
Oh. The guards at Green Manors.
The patient was playing cards,
now no longer blank...
a game of 21 with a bearded man
who was evidently Dr. Edwardes.
Yes, one usually dreams of one's
analyst as an authority with a beard.
He dealt Edwardes the seven
of clubs, and Edwardes said...
"That makes it 21."
I would say the patient
was trying to mention a locale.
The seven of clubs
might mean a club.
Yes, with the word 21 in it.
There is such a place in New York.
It's called the 21 Club.
I've heard of it.
The patient dreamt
the proprietor of the place came in...
and began accusing
Dr. Edwardes of cheating.
He ordered Edwardes out and said,
"I won't allow you to play here.
This is my place.
I'm going to fix you."
The dream gives the locale
a double identity...
the 21 Club and Green Manors.
But the proprietor seems
to belong more to the latter.
In fact...
I would say that
this angry proprietor...
who threatened Dr. Edwardes...
was myself.
It seemed that way to me.
I presume you only arrived
at this solution tonight.
Yes.
And have confided your
psychoanalytic findings to nobody.
Not yet.
Was there any more
to the dream?
Yes. The patient dreamt he
and Dr. Edwardes...
were on a high-sloping roof...
and that he saw Edwardes plunge
over the edge to his death.
He also saw the angry proprietor
hiding behind the chimney, laughing...
holding a small wheel
in his hand.
He dropped the wheel.
The symbolism of the small wheel
escapes me.
It was a revolver.
The proprietor who threatened
Edwardes' life in the 21 Club...
dropped a revolver in the snow
in Gabriel Valley after shooting
The weapon is still there
at the foot of a tree...
with the murderer's
fingerprints on it.
I can't agree with this part
of your interpretation...
for the good reason that
the weapon is now in my hand.
I imagined something
of this sort would happen...
when I made the slip tonight
about knowing Edwardes.
That started your agile
young mind going.
You were having a breakdown.
And in a state of panic, you heard that
Edwardes was to take your place here.
So you sought him out in his
favorite restaurant where he was
You accused him
of stealing your job.
You threatened to kill him.
He calmed you down, told you he
was off on a skiing vacation.
You followed him there...
and shot him from behind a tree.
That's enough.
Your story is ridiculous.
You'll make a fool of yourself...
a love-smitten analyst
playing a dream detective.
There'll be no dreams
for the police.
They'll find out from the waitress
in the 21 Club that you were there.
You'll be identified as the man
who had a row with Dr. Edwardes.
There'll be people who saw you
on the train to Gabriel Valley,
There will be no dreams
necessary for this case.
I see.
You're an excellent analyst,
Dr. Petersen, but a rather stupid woman.
What did you think I'd do when you
told me all this? Congratulate you?
You forget in your imbecilic
devotion to your patient...
that the punishment
for two murders...
is the same as for one.
You're not going to commit
a second murder, Dr. Murchison.
I hadn't planned to.
But you're here.
You're not leaving.
A man with your intelligence
does not commit a stupid murder.
You're thinking you're not
mentally responsible for that
They'll find extenuating circumstances
in the state of your health.
They'll not execute you
for the death of Dr. Edwardes.
You can still live,
read, write, research...
even if you are put away.
You're thinking that now,
Dr. Murchison.
If you shoot now,
it is cold, deliberate murder.
You'll be tried
as a sane murderer...
convicted as a sane man...
and killed in the electric chair
for your crime.
I'm going to telephone
the police now, Dr. Murchison.
[Laughing]
And remember what I say.
Any husband of Constance
is a husband of mine, so to speak.
- All right. Good-bye. Good luck.
- Good-bye.