[***]
GANDALF:
You cannot pass!
FRODO:
Gandalf!
GANDALF: I am a servant
of the Secret Fire,
wielder of the flame of Anor.
Go back to the Shadows.
The dark fire will not avail
you, flame of Udun!
You shall not pass!
No! No!
Gandalf!
Fly, you fools.
No!
FRODO:
Gandalf!
[BALROG GROWLS]
[GANDALF YELLS]
Gandalf!
What is it, Mr. Frodo?
Nothing.
Just a dream.
Mordor. The one place
in Middle-earth
we don't want to see any closer.
And it's the one place
we're trying to get to.
It's just where we can't get.
Let's face it,
Mr. Frodo, we're lost.
I don't think Gandalf meant
for us to come this way.
He didn't mean for a lot
of things to happen, Sam.
But they did.
[GROWLING]
Mr. Frodo?
It's the Ring, isn't it?
It's getting heavier.
What food have we got left?
Well, let me see.
Oh, yes. Lovely.
Lembas bread. And look!
More lembas bread.
I don't usually hold
with foreign food
but this Elvish stuff,
it's not bad.
Nothing ever dampens your
spirits, does it, Sam?
Those rain clouds might.
This looks
strangely familiar.
It's because we've
been here before.
We're going in circles.
SAM:
What is that horrid stink?
I warrant there's
a nasty bog nearby.
Can you smell it?
Yes.
I can smell it.
We're not alone.
The thieves. The thieves.
The filthy little thieves.
Where is it?
They stole it from us.
My precious.
Curse them, we hates them!
It's ours, it is,
and we wants it!
This is Sting.
You've seen it before,
haven't you, Gollum?
Release him
or I'll cut your throat.
[SCREAMING ECHOES]
It burns!
It burns us!
It freezes!
Nasty Elves twisted it.
Take it off us!
Quiet, you!
It's hopeless.
Every Orc in Mordor's going
to hear this racket.
Let's just tie him up
and leave him.
No!
That would kill us!
Kill us!
It's no more than you deserve!
Maybe he does deserve to die.
But now that I see him,
I do pity him.
We be nice to them
if they be nice to us.
Take it off us.
We swears to do what you wants.
We swears.
There's no promise you can make
that I can trust.
We swears,
to serve the master
of the precious.
We will swear on...
On the precious!
Gollum. Gollum.
The Ring is treacherous.
It will hold you to your word.
Yes...
...on the precious.
On the precious.
I don't believe you!
Get down! I said, down!
Sam!
He's trying to trick us.
If we let him go,
he'll throttle us in our sleep.
You know the way to Mordor?
Yes.
You've been there before?
You will lead us
to the Black Gate.
Merry!
What is it? What do you smell?
Man-flesh.
Aragorn.
They've picked up our trail.
Let's move!
Their pace has quickened.
They must have caught our scent.
Hurry!
Come on, Gimli!
Three days and nights pursuit.
No food. No rest.
And no sign of our quarry,
but what bare rock can tell.
Not idly do
the leaves of Lorien fall.
They may yet be alive.
Less than a day
ahead of us. Come.
Come, Gimli!
We're gaining on them!
I'm wasted on cross-country.
We Dwarves
are natural sprinters.
Very dangerous
over short distances.
Rohan.
Home of the Horse-lords.
There's something
strange at work here.
Some evil gives speed
to these creatures.
Sets its will against us.
ARAGORN: Legolas!
What do your Elf-eyes see?
The Uruks turn northeast.
They are taking
the Hobbits to Isengard.
Saruman.
[METAL CLANGING]
SARUMAN:
The world is changing.
Who now has the strength
to stand against the armies
of Isengard
and Mordor?
To stand against the might
of Sauron and Saruman
and the union
of the two towers?
Together, my Lord Sauron
we shall rule
this Middle-earth.
[GROWLING AND SCREECHING]
The Old World will burn
in the fires of industry.
The forests will fall.
A new order will rise.
We will drive the machine
of war with the sword
and the spear
and the iron fists of the Orc.
We have only to remove
those who oppose us.
The Horse-Men took your lands.
They drove your people
into the hills
to scratch a living off rocks.
Murderers!
Take back the lands
they stole from you.
Burn every village!
SARUMAN:
It will begin in Rohan.
Too long have these peasants
stood against you.
But no more.
Eothain! Eothain!
You take your sister.
You'll go faster with just two.
Papa says Eothain
must not ride Garulf.
He is too big for him.
Listen to me.
You must ride to Edoras
and raise the alarm.
Do you understand me?
Yes, Mama.
I don't want to leave.
I don't want to go, Mama.
Freda, I will find you there.
[SCREAMING]
Quickly!
Go, child.
SARUMAN:
Rohan, my lord
is ready to fall.
Theodred.
EOWYN: Your son
is badly wounded, my lord.
He was ambushed by Orcs.
If we don't defend our country,
Saruman will take it by force.
That is a lie.
Saruman the White has ever been
our friend and ally.
Grima.
Orcs are roaming freely
across our lands.
Unchecked. Unchallenged.
Killing at will.
Orcs bearing
the White Hand of Saruman.
Why do you lay these troubles
on an already troubled mind?
Can you not see?
Your uncle is wearied
by your malcontent,
your warmongering.
Warmongering?
How long is it since
Saruman bought you?
What was
the promised price, Grima?
When all the Men are dead,
you will take your share
of the treasure?
Too long have
you watched my sister.
you haunted her steps.
You see much, Eomer,
son of Eomund.
Too much.
You are banished forthwith
from the kingdom of Rohan
under pain of death.
[***]
Keep breathing. That's the key.
Breathe.
They've run as if the very whips
of their masters
were behind them.
We're not going no further
until we've had a breather.
Get a fire going!
Merry!
I think we might
have made a mistake
leaving the Shire, Pippin.
[TREES GROANING]
What's making that noise?
It's the trees.
What?
You remember the Old Forest,
on the borders of Buckland?
Folk used to say there was
something in the water
that made the trees grow tall
and come alive.
Alive?
Trees that could whisper,
talk to each other,
even move.
I'm starving.
We ain't had nothing but maggoty
bread for three stinking days.
Yeah!
Why can't we have some meat?!
What about them?
They're fresh.
They are not for eating.
What about their legs?
They don't need those.
Ooh, they look tasty.
Get back, scum!
Carve them up!
Just a mouthful.
No!
Looks like meat's back
on the menu, boys.
Pippin.
Let's go.
Go on.
Call for help.
Squeal.
No one's going to save you now.
[HORSE WHINNIES]
Pippin!
A red sun rises.
Blood has
been spilled this night.
Riders of Rohan,
what news from the Mark?
What business does an Elf,
a Man and a Dwarf have
in the Riddermark?
Speak quickly!
Give me your name, horse-master,
and I shall give you mine.
I would cut off your head,
Dwarf,
if it stood but a little higher
from the ground.
You would die before
your stroke fell.
I am Aragorn, son of Arathorn.
This is Gimli, son of Gloin,
and Legolas
of the Woodland Realm.
We are friends of Rohan
and of Theoden, your king.
Theoden no longer recognizes
friend from foe.
Not even his own kin.
Saruman has poisoned the mind
of the king
and claimed lordship
over these lands.
My company
are those loyal to Rohan.
And for that, we are banished.
The White Wizard is cunning.
He walks here
and there, they say,
as an old man hooded
and cloaked.
And everywhere, his spies
slip past our nets.
We are no spies.
We track a party of Uruk-hai
westward across the plain.
They have taken two
of our friends captive.
The Uruks are destroyed.
We slaughtered
them during the night.
But there were two Hobbits.
Did you see two
Hobbits with them?
They would be small.
Only children to your eyes.
We left none alive.
We piled the carcasses
and burned them.
Dead?
I am sorry.
[WHISTLING]
Hasufel! Arod!
May these horses bear you
to better fortune
than their former masters.
Farewell.
Look for your friends.
But do not trust to hope.
It has forsaken these lands.
We ride north!
It's one of their wee belts.
[SPEAKING ELVISH]
Ahh!
We failed them.
A Hobbit lay here.
And the other.
They crawled.
Their hands were bound.
Their bonds were cut.
They ran over here.
They were followed.
MERRY: The belt!
MERRY: Run!
Tracks lead away
from the battle...
into Fangorn Forest.
Fangorn?
What madness
drove them in there?
PIPPIN:
Did we lose him?
I think we lost him.
[SNARLING
AND BRANCHES SNAPPING]
I'm going to rip out
your filthy little innards!
Come here!
Trees. Climb a tree.
He's gone.
[GRUNTS]
Merry!
[GROANS]
[YELLS]
Let's put a maggot hole
in your belly!
Run, Merry!
[GRUNTING]
Little Orcs,
bru-ra-hroom.
It's talking, Merry.
The tree is talking.
Tree?
I am no tree!
I am an Ent.
A tree-herder.
A shepherd of the forest.
Don't talk to it, Merry.
Don't encourage it!
Treebeard, some call me.
And whose side are you on?
Side?
I am on nobody's side...
because nobody's on my side,
little Orc.
Nobody cares
for the woods anymore.
We're not Orcs!
We're Hobbits!
Hobbits? Hmm.
Never heard
of a Hobbit before.
Sounds like
Orc mischief to me!
[GRIP TIGHTENING]
They come with fire.
They come with axes.
Gnawing, biting, breaking,
hacking, burning!
Destroyers and usurpers!
Curse them!
No!
You don't understand.
We're Hobbits! Halflings!
Shire-folk!
Maybe you are...
and maybe you aren't.
The White Wizard will know.
The White Wizard?
Saruman.
See? See?
We've led you out.
Hurry, Hobbitses.
Hurry!
Very lucky
we find you.
Nice Hobbit.
[SAM YELLS]
It's a bog.
He's led us
into a swamp.
A swamp, yes, yes.
Come, master. We will take you
on safe paths through the mist.
Come, Hobbits! Come!
We go quickly.
GOLLUM:
I found it. I did.
The way through the marshes.
Orcs don't use it.
Orcs don't know it.
They go around
for miles and miles.
Come quickly.
Soft and quick as shadows
we must be.
There are dead things!
Dead faces in the water.
All dead.
All rotten.
Elves and Men
and Orcses.
A great battle long ago.
Dead Marshes.
Yes. Yes, that is their name.
This way.
Don't follow the lights.
[GRUNTS]
Careful now! Or Hobbits go down
to join the dead ones
and light little candles
of their own.
[VOICES WHISPERING AND WAILING]
Frodo!
[PANTING AND GRUNTING]
Gollum?
Don't follow the lights.
Gollum!
Mr. Frodo!
Are you all right?
[RUMBLING]
So bright.
So beautiful.
Our precious.
What did you say?
Master should be resting.
Master needs to keep up
his strength.
Who are you?
Mustn't ask us.
Not its business.
Gollum. Gollum.
Gandalf told me you were
one of the river-folk.
* Cold be heart
And hand and bone *
* Cold be travelers
Far from home *
He said your life
was a sad story.
* They do not see
What lies ahead *
* When sun has failed
And moon is dead **
You were not so very different
from a Hobbit once.
Were you?
Smeagol.
What did you call me?
A long time ago.
My name.
S...
Smeagol.
[RINGWRAITH SCREECHES]
[YELLS]
Black Riders!
Hide! Hide!
[YELLS]
Come on, Frodo. Come on!
GOLLUM:
Quick! They will see us!
They will see us!
I thought they were dead.
Dead?
No, you cannot kill them. No.
[RINGWRAITH SCREECHES]
[SNIFFING]
[YELLS
AND RINGWRAITH SCREECHES]
Wraiths!
Wraiths on wings!
[RINGWRAITH SCREECHES]
They are calling for it.
They are calling
for the precious.
Mr. Frodo! It's all right.
I'm here.
[RINGWRAITH SCREECHES]
[FELL BEAST ROARS]
Hurry, Hobbits.
The Black Gate is very close.
[SNIFFS AND SPITS]
Orc blood.
These are strange tracks.
The air is so close in here.
This forest is old.
Very old.
Full of memory...
[TREES GROANING]
and anger.
[CREAKING]
The trees are speaking
to each other.
Gimli!
Lower your ax.
Oh.
Aragorn,
[IN ELVISH]
The White Wizard
approaches.
Do not let him speak.
He will put a spell on us.
We must be quick.
[YELLS]
WHITE WIZARD:
You are tracking the footsteps
of two young Hobbits.
Where are they?
They passed this way
the day before yesterday.
They met someone
they did not expect.
Does that comfort you?
Who are you?
Show yourself!
It cannot be.
You fell.
Through fire...
and water.
From the lowest dungeon
to the highest peak,
I fought with the Balrog
of Morgoth.
[BALROG GRUNTS]
Until at last I threw down
my enemy,
and smote his ruin
upon the mountainside.
Darkness took me,
and I strayed out of thought
and time.
Stars wheeled overhead,
and every day was as long
as a life age of the Earth.
But it was not the end.
I felt life in me again.
[GASPS]
I've been sent back,
until my task is done.
Gandalf.
Gandalf?
Yes.
That was what
they used to call me.
Gandalf the Grey.
That was my name.
Gandalf.
I am Gandalf the White.
And I come back to you now...
at the turn of the tide.
GANDALF:
One stage of your journey
is over. Another begins.
War has come to Rohan.
We must ride to Edoras
with all speed.
[WHISTLING]
[SHADOWFAX NEIGHS]
That is one of the Mearas,
unless my eyes are cheated
by some spell.
GANDALF: Shadowfax.
He is the lord of all horses...
and has been my friend
through many dangers.
TREEBEARD:
My home lies deep
in the forest
near the roots of the mountain.
I told Gandalf
I would keep you safe.
And safe is where I'll keep you.
The trees have grown wild
and dangerous.
Anger festers in their hearts.
They will harm you if they can.
There are too few of us now.
Too few of us Ents
left to manage them.
GOLLUM:
The Black Gate of Mordor.
Oh, save us.
My old Gaffer would have
a thing or two to say
if he could see us now.
Master says to show him
the way into Mordor.
So good Smeagol does,
master says so.
I did.
That's it, then.
We can't get past that.
[EASTERLINGS
YELLING INDISTINCTLY]
[YELLING AND DRUMMING]
[HORN BLOWS]
[BLOWS HORN]
[SCREECHES]
Look!
The gate.
It's opening!
I can see
a way down.
Sam, no!
[YELLS]
Master!
[ROCKS FALLING]
[DRUMMING]
[EASTERLINGS
YELLING INDISTINCTLY]
I do not ask you
to come with me, Sam.
I know, Mr. Frodo.
I doubt even these Elvish cloaks
will hide us in there.
Now!
No!
No! No, master!
They catch you!
Don't take it to him.
He wants the precious.
Always he is looking for it.
And the precious is wanting
to go back to him.
But we mustn't
let him have it.
No! There's another way.
More secret.
A dark way.
Why haven't you spoken
of this before?
Because master
did not ask.
He's up to something.
Are you saying there's
another way into Mordor?
Yes. There's a path,
and some stairs.
And then...
a tunnel.
[GATE CREAKING]
He's led us this far, Sam.
Mr. Frodo, no.
He's been true to his word.
No.
Lead the way, Smeagol.
Good Smeagol always helps.
[GATES CLANG SHUT]
GANDALF:
Edoras and the Golden Hall
of Meduseld.
There dwells Theoden,
King of Rohan,
whose mind is overthrown.
Saruman's hold over
King Theoden
is now very strong.
EOWYN:
My lord, your son...
he is dead.
My lord?
Uncle?
Will you not go to him?
Will you do nothing?
Be careful what you say.
Do not look for welcome here.
Oh, he must have died
sometime in the night.
What a tragedy
for the king
to lose his only
son and heir.
Especially now that your brother
has deserted you.
Leave me alone, snake!
Oh, but you are alone.
Who knows what you've spoken
to the darkness...
in the bitter watches
of the night...
when all your life
seems to shrink.
The walls of your bower
closing in about you.
A hutch to trammel
some wild thing in.
So fair.
So cold.
Like a morning
of pale spring
still clinging
to winter's chill.
Your words are poison.
[***]
You'll find more cheer
in a graveyard.
Ah.
I cannot allow you before
Theoden King so armed,
Gandalf Greyhame.
By order of Grima Wormtongue.
Your staff.
You would not part an old man
from his walking stick.
My lord,
Gandalf the Grey is coming.
He's a herald of woe.
The courtesy of your hall
is somewhat lessened of late,
Theoden King.
He's not welcome.
Why should I welcome you
Gandalf Stormcrow?
A just question, my liege.
Late is the hour
in which this conjurer
chooses to appear.
Lathspell I name him.
Ill news is an ill guest.
Be silent.
Keep your forked tongue
behind your teeth.
I have not passed
through fire and death
to bandy crooked words
with a witless worm.
His staff.
I told you to take
the wizard's staff.
Theoden,
son of Thengel,
too long have you sat
in the Shadows.
I would stay still
if I were you.
Hearken to me!
I release you
from the spell.
[LAUGHS]
You have no power here,
Gandalf the Grey.
I will draw you, Saruman,
as poison is drawn from a wound.
Wait.
SARUMAN'S VOICE:
If I go, Theoden dies.
You did not kill me,
you will not kill him.
Rohan is mine.
Be gone.
I know your face.
Eowyn.
Gandalf?
Breathe the free air again,
my friend.
Dark have been
my dreams of late.
Your fingers would remember
their old strength better
if they grasped your sword.
Ah, ah!
I've only...
...ever served you, my lord.
Your leechcraft would
have had me crawling
on all fours like a beast!
Send me not from your sight.
No, my lord! No, my lord.
Let him go.
Enough blood has been spilt
on his account.
Get out of my way!
Hail, Theoden King!
Where is Theodred?
Where is my son?
Simbelmyne.
Ever has it grown on the tombs
of my forebearers.
Now it shall cover the grave
of my son.
Alas that these evil days
should be mine.
The young perish
and the old linger.
That I should live
to see the last days
of my house.
Theodred's death
was not of your making.
No parent should have to bury
their child.
He was strong in life.
His spirit will find its way
to the halls of your fathers.
[SPEAKING ROHIRRIM]
They had no warning.
They were unarmed.
Now the Wild Men
are moving through the Westfold,
burning as they go.
Rick, cot and tree.
Where is Mama?
Shh.
This is but a taste
of the terror
that Saruman will unleash.
All the more potent for he is
driven now by fear of Sauron.
Ride out and meet him head-on.
Draw him away
from your women and children.
You must fight.
You have 2000 good men riding
north as we speak.
Eomer is loyal to you.
His men will return
and fight for their king.
They will be 300 leagues
from here by now.
Eomer cannot help us.
I know what it is
you want of me
but I will not bring further
death to my people.
I will not risk open war.
Open war is upon you, whether
you would risk it or not.
When last I looked
Theoden, not Aragorn,
was king of Rohan.
[BELCHES]
Then what is the king's
decision?
By order of the king
the city must empty.
We make for the refuge
of Helm's Deep.
Do not burden yourself
with treasures.
Take only what
provisions you need.
Helm's Deep.
They flee to the mountains
when they should
stand and fight.
Who will defend them if not
their king?
He's only doing what he thinks
is best for his people.
Helm's Deep has saved them
in the past.
There is no way out
of that ravine.
Theoden is walking into a trap.
He thinks he's leading
them to safety.
What they will get
is a massacre.
Theoden has a strong will,
but I fear for him.
I fear for the survival
of Rohan.
He will need you
before the end, Aragorn.
The people of Rohan
will need you.
The defenses have to hold.
They will hold.
The Grey Pilgrim.
That's what they
used to call me.
Three hundred lives of Men
I've walked this earth,
and now I have no time.
With luck, my search
will not be in vain.
Look to my coming at first light
on the fifth day.
At dawn, look to the east.
Go.
[***]
You have some skill
with a blade.
Women of this country
learned long ago:
Those without swords
can still die upon them.
I fear neither death nor pain.
What do you fear, my lady?
A cage.
To stay behind bars until use
and old age accept them.
And all chance
of valor has gone
beyond recall or desire.
You're a daughter of kings,
a shieldmaiden of Rohan.
I do not think
that would be your fate.
[***]
Theoden will not
stay at Edoras.
It's vulnerable. He knows this.
He will expect an attack
on the city.
They will flee to Helm's Deep
the great fortress of Rohan.
WORMTONGUE:
It is a dangerous road to take
through the mountains.
They will be slow.
They will have women
and children with them.
Send out your Warg-riders.
Hey, stinker, don't go getting
too far ahead.
Why do you do that?
What?
Call him names.
Run him down all the time.
Because.
Because that's
what he is, Mr. Frodo.
There's naught left in him
but lies and deceit.
It's the Ring he wants.
It's all he cares about.
You have no idea what
it did to him...
...what it's still doing to him.
I want to help him, Sam.
Why?
Because I have to believe
he can come back.
You can't save him, Mr. Frodo.
What do you know about it?
Nothing!
I'm sorry, Sam. I don't know
why I said that.
I do.
It's the Ring.
You can't take your eyes off it.
I've seen you.
You're not eating.
You barely sleep.
It's taken hold
of you, Mr. Frodo.
You have to fight it.
I know what I have to do, Sam.
The Ring was entrusted to me.
It's my task.
Mine! My own!
Can't you hear yourself?
Don't you know who
you sound like?
We wants it.
We needs it.
Must have the precious.
They stole it from us.
Sneaky little Hobbitses.
Wicked. Tricksy. False.
No. Not master.
Yes, precious. False.
They will cheat you,
hurt you, lie!
Master's my friend.
You don't have any friends.
Nobody likes you.
Not listening.
I'm not listening.
You're a liar and a thief.
No.
Murderer.
Go away.
Go away?
I hate you.
Where would you be without me?
Gollum. Gollum.
I saved us.
It was me.
We survived because of me.
Not anymore.
What did you say?
Master looks after us now.
We don't need you.
What?
Leave now,
and never come back.
No.
Leave now and never come back.
Leave now and never come back!
We told him to go away.
And away he goes, precious.
Gone! Gone! Gone!
Smeagol is free!
Look.
Look. See what Smeagol finds?
They are young.
They are tender. They are nice.
Yes, they are.
Eat them. Eat them!
You'll make him sick,
you will,
behaving like that.
There's only one way to eat
a brace of coneys.
[GOLLUM SQUEALING]
What's it doing?
Stupid, fat Hobbit.
It ruins it.
What's to ruin?
There's hardly any meat on them.
[BIRD SQUAWKING]
What we need
is a few good taters.
What's taters, precious?
What's taters? Eh?
Po-ta-toes.
Boil them, mash them,
stick them in a stew.
Lovely, big, golden chips
with a nice piece of fried fish.
Even you couldn't
say no to that.
Oh, yes, we could.
Spoil a nice fish.
Give it to us raw,
and wriggling.
You keep nasty chips.
You're hopeless.
Mr. Frodo?
SAM:
Who are they?
Wicked Men.
Servants of Sauron.
They are called to Mordor.
The Dark One is gathering
all armies to him.
it won't be long now.
He will soon be ready.
Ready to do what?
To make his war.
The last war that will cover
all the world in Shadow.
We've got to get moving.
Come on, Sam.
Mr. Frodo.
Look.
It's an oliphaunt.
No one at home
will believe this.
Smeagol?
Ah!
We've lingered here too long.
Come on, Sam.
Bind their hands.
It's true, you don't see
many Dwarf women.
And in fact, they are so alike
in voice and appearance
that they're often mistaken
for Dwarf men.
It's the beards.
This, in turn, has given rise
to the belief
that there are no Dwarf women
and that Dwarves just spring out
of holes in the ground,
which is, of course, ridiculous.
It's all right. Nobody panic.
That was deliberate.
It was deliberate.
ARWEN: The light of the Evenstar
does not wax and wane.
It is mine to give
to whom I will.
Like my heart.
Go to sleep.
I am asleep.
This is a dream.
Then it is a good dream.
Sleep.
[SPEAKING IN ELVISH]
Arwen...
Where is she?
Our time here is ending.
Arwen's time is ending.
Let her go.
Let her take the ship
into the west.
Let her bear away her love
for you to the Undying Lands.
There it will be ever green.
But never more than memory.
I will not leave my daughter
here to die.
She stays because
she still has hope.
She stays for you.
She belongs with her people.
[SPEAKING ELVISH]
Why are you saying this?
I am mortal. You are Elf-kind.
It was a dream, Arwen.
Nothing more.
This belongs to you.
It was a gift.
Keep it.
My lord?
She is sailing
to the Undying Lands
with all that
is left of her kin.
What is it?
Hama?
I'm not sure.
Wargs!
A scout!
What is it? What do you see?
Warg! We're under attack!
Get them out of here!
All riders to the head
of the column.
Come on. Get me up here.
I'm a rider.
Come on!
You must lead the people
to Helm's Deep, and make haste.
I can fight.
No!
You must do this, for me.
Follow me!
Forward. I mean, charge forward.
Make for the lower ground!
That's it! Go on!
Stay together!
Bring your pretty face to my ax.
That one counts as mine!
Stinking creature.
Aragorn!
Aragorn?
[SHARKU LAUGHS]
[COUGHS]
[LAUGHING AND GRUNTING]
Tell me what happened
and I will ease your passing.
He's...
[COUGHS]
dead.
He took a little tumble
off the cliff.
You lie.
[LAUGHING AND CHOKING]
Get the wounded on horses.
The wolves of Isengard
will return.
Leave the dead.
Come.
WOMAN 1: At last!
WOMAN 2: Helm's Deep.
WOMAN 3:
There it is, Helm's Deep.
WOMAN 4:
We're safe!
We're safe,
my lady.
Thank you.
[***]
Mama!
MORWEN: Eothain!
Freda!
GAMLING:
Make way for Theoden.
Make way for the king.
So few. So few of you
have returned.
Our people are safe.
We have paid for it
with many lives.
My lady.
Lord Aragorn...
where is he?
He fell.
THEODEN:
Draw all our forces
behind the wall.
Bar the gate.
And set a watch on the surround.
GAMLING:
What of those
who cannot fight, my lord?
The women and children?
THEODEN:
Get them into the caves.
Saruman's arm will
have grown long indeed
if he thinks
he can reach us here.
WORMTONGUE:
Helm's Deep has one weakness.
Its outer wall is solid rock,
but for a small culvert
at its base,
which is little more
than a drain.
How? How can fire
undo stone?
What kind of device
could bring down the wall?
If the wall is breached,
Helm's Deep will fall.
Even if it is breached,
it would take
a number beyond reckoning,
thousands,
to storm the Keep.
Tens of thousands.
But, my lord,
there is no such force.
[HORNS SOUNDING]
[ARMY CHEERING]
A new power is rising.
Its victory is at hand.
This night...
the land will be stained
with the blood of Rohan!
March to Helm's Deep!
Leave none alive!
To war!
There will be no dawn for Men.
Look. There's smoke
to the south.
There is always
smoke rising
from Isengard
these days.
Isengard?
There was a time
when Saruman would walk
in my woods.
But now he has
a mind of metal
and wheels.
He no longer cares
for growing things.
What is it?
[DISTANT HORN SOUNDING
AND FEET MARCHING]
It's Saruman's army.
The war has started.
[***]
ARWEN:
May the grace of the Valar
protect you.
Brego.
Arwen.
[SPEAKING IN ELVISH]
I have made my choice.
He is not coming back.
Why do you linger here
when there is no hope?
There is still hope.
If Aragorn survives this war,
you will still be parted.
If Sauron is defeated
and Aragorn made king,
and all that you hope for
comes true,
you will still have to taste
the bitterness of mortality.
Whether by the sword
or the slow decay of time,
Aragorn will die.
And there will be
no comfort for you,
no comfort to ease the pain
of his passing.
He will come to death,
an image of the splendor
of the kings of Men,
in glory undimmed before
the breaking of the world.
But you, my daughter...
you will linger on in darkness
and in doubt,
as nightfall in winter
that comes without a star.
Here you will dwell,
bound to your grief
under the fading trees...
until all the world is changed
and the long years of your life
are utterly spent.
Arwen.
There is nothing
for you here,
only death.
[GALADRIEL SPEAKING IN ELVISH]
[SPEAKING ELVISH]
GALADRIEL:
The power of the enemy
is growing.
Sauron will use his puppet,
Saruman
to destroy
the people of Rohan.
Isengard has been unleashed.
The Eye of Sauron
now turns to Gondor,
the last free kingdom of Men.
His war on this country
will come swiftly.
He senses the Ring is close.
The strength of the Ring-bearer
is failing.
In his heart,
Frodo begins to understand
the quest will claim his life.
You know this.
You have foreseen it.
It is the risk we all took.
In the gathering dark,
the will of the Ring
grows strong.
It works hard now to find its
way back into the hands of Men.
Men, who are so easily seduced
by its power.
The young captain of Gondor
has but to extend his hand,
take the Ring for his own,
and the world will fall.
It is close now.
So close to achieving its goal.
For Sauron will have dominion
over all life on this Earth,
even unto to the ending
of the world.
The time of the Elves...
is over.
Do we leave Middle-earth
to its fate?
Do we let them stand alone?
What news?
Our scouts report Saruman
has attacked Rohan.
Theoden's people have fled
to Helm's Deep.
But we must look
to our own borders.
Faramir,
Orcs are on the move.
Sauron is marshaling
an army.
Easterlings and Southrons
are at the Black Gate.
How many?
Some thousands.
More come every day.
Who's covering the river
to the north?
We pulled 500 men
at Osgiliath.
If their city is attacked,
we won't hold it.
Saruman attacks
from Isengard.
Sauron from Mordor.
The fight will come to Men
on both fronts.
Gondor is weak.
Sauron will strike us soon.
And he will strike hard.
He knows now we do not have
the strength to repel him.
My men tell me
that you are Orc spies.
Spies?! Now wait just a minute.
Well, if you're not spies,
then who are you?
Speak.
We are Hobbits
of the Shire.
Frodo Baggins is my name,
and this is Samwise Gamgee.
Your bodyguard?
His gardener.
And where is your
skulking friend?
That gangrel creature.
He had an ill-favored look.
There was no other.
We set out from Rivendell
with seven companions.
One we lost in Moria...
two were my kin,
a Dwarf there was also.
And an Elf and two Men.
Aragorn, son of Arathorn,
and Boromir of Gondor.
You're a friend of Boromir?
Yes.
For my part.
It will grieve you then
to learn that he is dead.
Dead?
How? When?
As one of his companions,
I'd hoped you would tell me.
He was my brother.
Captain Faramir!
[WHISPERING]
We found the third one.
[FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING]
You must come with me. Now.
Down there.
To enter the Forbidden Pool
bears the penalty of death.
They wait for my command.
Shall I shoot?
* The rock and pool
Is nice and cool *
* So juicy sweet *
* Our only wish
To catch a fish *
* So juicy sweet **
[YELLS]
Wait.
This creature is bound to me.
And I to him.
He is our guide.
Please...
let me go down to him.
[GRUNTS]
Smeagol.
[SPITS]
Master is here.
Come, Smeagol.
Trust master. Come.
We must go now?
Smeagol, you must trust master.
Follow me. Come on.
Come.
Come, Smeagol.
Nice Smeagol. That's it.
Come on.
[FOOTSTEP]
Don't hurt him!
[YELLING]
Smeagol, don't struggle.
Smeagol, listen to me.
Master!
[MUFFLED CRIES]
No! No!
[GRUNTING
AND PANTING]
Where are you leading them?
[CRYING]
Answer me.
GOLLUM:
Smeagol.
[CRYING]
Why does it cry,
Smeagol?
SMEAGOL:
Cruel Men hurts us.
Master tricksed us.
GOLLUM:
Of course he did.
I told you he was tricksy.
I told you he was false.
SMEAGOL:
Master is our friend.
Our friend.
GOLLUM:
Master betrayed us.
SMEAGOL:
No. Not its business.
Leave us alone!
GOLLUM:
Filthy little Hobbitses!
They stole it from us!
SMEAGOL:
No. No.
What did they steal?
GOLLUM:
My precious!
[YELLS]
We have to
get out of here.
You go. Go, now.
You can do it.
Use the Ring,
Mr. Frodo.
Just this once.
Put it on.
Disappear.
I can't.
You were right, Sam.
You tried to tell me but...
I'm sorry.
The Ring's taking me, Sam.
If I put it on,
he'll find me.
He'll see.
Mr. Frodo...
So this is the answer
to all the riddles.
Here in the Wild
I have you,
two Halflings,
and a host of Men at my call.
The Ring of Power
within my grasp.
A chance for Faramir,
captain of Gondor...
to show his quality.
[VOICE OF THE RING
WHISPERING]
No!
Stop it!
Leave him alone.
Don't you understand?
He's got to destroy it!
That's where we're going,
into Mordor.
To the Mountain of Fire!
Osgiliath is under attack.
They call for reinforcements.
SAM:
Please. It's such a burden.
Will you not help him?
Captain?
Prepare to leave.
The Ring will go to Gondor.
[DISTANT MARCHING
FOOTSTEPS]
[***]
[SPEAKING ELVISH]
WOMAN: He's alive!
Where is he?
Get out of the way!
I'm going to kill him!
You are the luckiest,
the canniest,
and the most reckless man
I ever knew.
Bless you, laddie.
Gimli, where is the king?
[SPEAKING IN ELVISH]
You look terrible.
[DOORS OPENING]
A great host, you say?
All Isengard
is emptied.
How many?
Ten thousand strong
at least.
Ten thousand?
It is an army bred
for a single purpose:
To destroy the world of Men.
They will be here by nightfall.
Let them come!
I want every man and strong lad
able to bear arms
to be ready for battle
by nightfall.
[HAMMERING]
MAN: Cross brace.
We will cover the causeway
and the gate from above.
No army has ever breached
the Deeping Wall
or set foot
inside the Hornburg!
This is no rabble
of mindless Orcs.
These are Uruk-hai.
Their armour is thick
and their shields broad.
I have fought many wars,
Master Dwarf.
I know how to defend
my own keep.
They will break upon this
fortress like water on rock.
Saruman's hordes
will pillage and burn.
We've seen it before.
Crops can be resown,
homes rebuilt.
Within these walls...
we will outlast them.
They do not come to destroy
Rohan's crops or villages.
They come to destroy
its people,
down to the last child.
What would you have me do?
Look at my men.
Their courage hangs
by a thread.
If this is to be our end,
then I would have them
make such an end
as to be worthy
of remembrance.
Send out riders,
my lord.
You must call for aid.
And who will come?
Elves?
Dwarves?
We are not so lucky
in our friends as you.
The old alliances are dead.
Gondor will answer.
Gondor?!
Where was Gondor
when the Westfold fell?!
Where was Gondor when our
enemies closed in around us?!
Where was Gon--?
No, my Lord Aragorn...
we are alone.
Get the women and children
into the caves.
We need more time
to lay provisions--
There is no time.
War is upon us.
Secure the gate.
[CAWING]
We Ents have not troubled
about the wars
of Men and wizards
for a very long time.
But now, something
is about to happen
that has not happened
for an age.
Entmoot.
What's that?
'Tis a gathering.
A gathering of what?
[RUMBLING]
Beech. Oak.
Chestnut. Ash.
Good. Good. Good.
Many have come.
Now we must decide
if the Ents
will go to war.
GUARD 1:
Move back! Move to the caves!
GUARD 1: Keep moving.
GUARD 2: Quickly now.
[BABY CRYING]
[***]
[CHATTERING INDISTINCTLY]
Farmers, farriers, stable boys.
These are no soldiers.
Most have seen
too many winters.
Or too few.
Look at them.
They're frightened.
You can see it in their eyes.
[SPEAKING IN ELVISH]
Aragorn.
Then I shall die as one of them!
Let him go, lad.
Let him be.
Every villager
able to wield a sword
has been sent
to the armoury.
My lord?
Who am I, Gamling?
You are our king, sire.
And do you trust your king?
Your men, my lord...
will follow you
to whatever end.
To whatever end.
Where is the horse
and the rider?
Where is the horn
that was blowing?
They have passed like rain
on the mountains.
Like wind in the meadow.
The days have gone down
in the West...
behind the hills...
into Shadow.
How did it come to this?
GUARD:
Move! Move to the outer wall.
Give me your sword.
What is your name?
Haleth, son of Hama, my lord.
The men are saying
we will not live out the night.
They say that it is hopeless.
This is a good sword.
Haleth, son of Hama...
there is always hope.
We have trusted you this far.
You have not led us astray.
Forgive me.
I was wrong to despair.
[SPEAKING IN ELVISH]
We had time,
I'd get this adjusted.
It's a little tight
across the chest.
[HORN SOUNDING]
That is no Orc horn.
[HORN SOUNDS]
Send for the king.
Open the gate!
GUARD:
Open up the gate!
How is this possible?
I bring word from Elrond
of Rivendell.
An alliance once existed
between Elves and Men.
Long ago we fought
and died together.
We come to honor
that allegiance.
[SPEAKING ELVISH]
You are most welcome.
We are proud to fight
alongside Men once more.
[MARCHING FOOTSTEPS
APPROACHING]
[INDISTINCT
GRUNTING AND GROWLING]
GIMLI:
You could have picked
a better spot.
Well, lad, whatever luck
you live by,
let's hope it lasts the night.
[THUNDERCLAP]
Your friends
are with you, Aragorn.
Let's hope they last the night.
[THUNDER RUMBLING]
[MARCHING FOOTSTEPS]
[BABY CRYING]
[SPEAKING IN ELVISH]
Ahh!
What's happening out there?
Shall I describe it to you?
Or would you like me
to find you a box?
[URAK-HAI BATTLE CRIES]
So it begins.
Did they hit anything?
Give them a volley.
Fire!
[SPEAKING ELVISH]
Send them to me! Come on!
Good!
Swords! Swords!
Legolas! Two already!
I'm on 17!
Huh?! I'll have no pointy-ear
outscoring me!
Nineteen!
[ENTS GROANING]
Merry.
We have just agreed.
Yes?
I have told your names
to the Entmoot
and we have agreed
you are not Orcs.
Well, that's good news.
And what about Saruman?
Have you come
to a decision about him?
Now, don't be hasty,
Master Meriadoc.
Hasty?
Our friends are out there.
They need our help. They cannot
fight this war on their own.
War? Yes.
It affects us all.
But you must understand,
young Hobbit
it takes a long time
to say anything in Old Entish
and we never say anything
unless it is worth taking
a long time to say.
Seventeen! Eighteen!
Nineteen!
Twenty!
Twenty-one!
Causeway!
[ARAGORN SHOUTS IN ELVISH]
Is this it?
Is this all you can conjure,
Saruman?
Brace the gate!
Hold them! Stand firm!
Aragorn!
Gimli!
[SPEAKING IN ELVISH]
The Ents cannot
hold back this storm.
We must weather such things
as we have always done.
How can that be your decision?!
This is not our war.
But you're part of this world!
Aren't you?!
[ENTS GRUMBLING]
You must help. Please.
You must do something.
You are young and brave,
Master Merry.
But your part
in this tale is over.
Go back to your home.
Maybe Treebeard's right.
We don't belong here, Merry.
It's too big for us.
What can we do in the end?
We've got the Shire.
Maybe we should go home.
The fires of Isengard
will spread
and the woods of Tuckborough
and Buckland will burn.
And...
And all that was once green and
good in this world will be gone.
There won't be a Shire, Pippin.
GAMLING:
Aragorn!
Fall back to the Keep!
Get your men out of there!
[SHOUTS IN ELVISH]
Haldir!
What are you doing?
What are you stopping for?
[SPEAKING IN ELVISH]
Haldir!
[***]
Brace the gate!
Hold them!
To the gate. Draw your swords!
Make way!
We cannot hold much longer!
Hold them!
How long do you need?
As long as you can give me.
Gimli!
Timbers!
Brace the gate!
Come on. We can take them.
It's a long way.
Toss me.
What?
I cannot jump the distance!
You'll have to toss me!
Don't tell the Elf.
Not a word.
Shore up the door!
Make way!
Follow me to the barricade.
Watch our backs!
Throw another one over here!
Higher!
Hold fast the gate!
Gimli! Aragorn!
Get out of there!
Aragorn!
Pull everybody back.
Pull them back.
Fall back!
They have broken through!
The castle is breached. Retreat!
Fall back!
Retreat!
ARAGORN:
Hurry! Inside. Get them inside!
GAMLING:
Into the Keep!
I will leave you at the western
borders of the forest.
You can make your way north
to your homeland from there.
Wait! Stop!
Stop!
Turn around.
Turn around. Take us south.
South?
But that will lead you
past Isengard.
Yes. Exactly.
If we go south, we can slip
past Saruman unnoticed.
The closer we are to danger,
the farther we are from harm.
It's the last thing
he'll expect.
That doesn't make sense to me.
But then
you are very small.
Perhaps you're right.
South it is, then.
Hold on, little Shirelings.
I always like going south.
Somehow it feels
like going downhill.
Are you mad? We'll be caught.
No, we won't.
Not this time.
Look!
Osgiliath burns!
Mordor has come.
The Ring will not save Gondor.
It has only
the power to destroy.
Please,
let me go.
Hurry.
Faramir!
You must let me go!
And those little family
of field mice
that climb up sometimes,
and they tickle me awfully.
They're always trying
to get somewhere where they--
Oh.
Many of these trees
were my friends.
Creatures I had known
from nut and acorn.
I'm sorry, Treebeard.
They had voices of their own.
Saruman.
A wizard should know better!
[TREEBEARD ROARS]
There is no curse in Elvish,
Entish or the tongues of Men
for this treachery.
with rock and stone.
[GROANING
AND FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING]
Yes.
Come, my friends.
The Ents are going to war.
It is likely
that we go to our doom.
Last march
of the Ents.
Faramir! Orcs have taken
the eastern shore.
Their numbers are too great.
By nightfall we will be overrun.
Mr. Frodo?
It's calling to him, Sam.
His Eye is almost on me.
Hold on, Mr. Frodo.
You'll be all right.
[MUTED SPEECH]
Take them to my father.
Tell him Faramir
sends a mighty gift.
A weapon that will change our
fortunes in this war.
Do you want to know
what happened to Boromir?
You want to know
why your brother died?
He tried to take
the Ring from Frodo,
after swearing an oath
to protect him!
He tried to kill him!
The Ring drove your brother mad!
ITHILIEN RANGER:
Watch out!
Mr. Frodo?
They're here.
They've come.
[RINGWRAITH SCREECHING]
Nazgul!
Stay here. Keep out of sight.
Take cover!
The fortress is taken.
It is over.
You said this fortress
would never fall
while your men defend it.
They still defend it.
They have died defending it.
WOMAN 1:
They're breaking in!
WOMAN 2:
They're past the door!
Is there no other way
for the women and children
to get out of the caves?
Is there no other way?
But they will not get far.
The Uruk-hai are too many.
Send word for the women
and children
to make for the mountain pass.
And barricade the entrance!
So much death.
What can Men do
against such reckless hate?
Ride out with me.
Ride out and meet them.
For death and glory.
For Rohan.
For your people.
The sun is rising.
GANDALF:
Look to my coming
at first light
on the fifth day.
At dawn,
look to the east.
Yes.
The horn of Helm Hammerhand
shall sound in the Deep...
one last time.
Yes!
Let this be the hour
when we draw swords together.
[***]
Fell deeds, awake.
Now for wrath,
now for ruin and a red dawn.
[HORN BLOWS]
Forth Eorlingas!
[BATTLE CRIES]
Gandalf.
Theoden King stands alone.
Not alone.
Rohirrim!
Eomer.
To the king!
Yes!
[GRUNTS]
TREEBEARD:
A hit. A fine hit.
[TREEBEARD GRUNTS]
[PANTS]
TREEBEARD:
Break the dam!
Release the river!
Pippin! Hold on!
[LAUGHS]
[GRUNTING]
Hold on, little Hobbits.
What are you doing?
Where are you going?
[ROARING]
It's me.
It's your Sam.
Don't you know your Sam?
[PANTING]
[SWORD CLANGING]
I can't do this, Sam.
I know.
It's all wrong.
By rights, we shouldn't
even be here.
[PANTS]
[THUNDER RUMBLES]
But we are.
It's like in the great stories,
Mr. Frodo.
The ones that really mattered.
Full of darkness
and danger they were.
And sometimes you didn't want
to know the end
because how could the end
be happy?
How could the world go back
to the way it was
when so much bad had happened?
Victory!
We have victory!
But in the end,
it's only a passing thing,
this shadow.
Even darkness must pass.
A new day will come.
And when the sun shines,
it will shine out the clearer.
Those were the stories
that stayed with you,
that meant something.
Even if you were too small
to understand why.
But I think, Mr. Frodo,
I do understand.
I know now.
Folk in those stories
had lots of chances of turning
back, only they didn't.
They kept going
because they were holding
on to something.
What are we holding on to, Sam?
That there's some good
in this world, Mr. Frodo.
And it's worth fighting for.
I think at last we understand
one another, Frodo Baggins.
You know the laws
of our country,
the laws of your father.
If you let them go,
your life will be forfeit.
Then it is forfeit.
Release them.
Sauron's wrath will be terrible,
his retribution swift.
[RUMBLING]
The battle for Helm's Deep
is over.
The battle for Middle-earth
is about to begin.
All our hopes now lie
with two little Hobbits...
somewhere in the wilderness.
I wonder if we'll ever be
put into songs or tales.
What?
I wonder if people
will ever say:
"Let's hear about Frodo
and the Ring."
And they'll say, "Yes! That's
one of my favorite stories."
"Frodo was really courageous,
wasn't he, Dad?"
"Yes, my boy.
The most famousest of Hobbits.
And that's saying a lot."
Well, you've left out
one of the chief characters:
"Samwise the Brave."
I want to hear more
about Sam.
Frodo wouldn't have got far
without Sam.
Now, Mr. Frodo,
you shouldn't make fun.
I was being serious.
So was I.
"Samwise the Brave."
FRODO:
Smeagol?
SAM:
We're not going to wait for you.
Come on.
Master.
Master looks after us.
Master wouldn't hurt us.
Master broke his promise.
Don't ask Smeagol.
Poor, poor Smeagol.
Master betrayed us.
Wicked. Tricksy. False.
We ought to wring
his filthy little neck.
Kill him! Kill him!
Kill them both!
And then we take the precious,
and we be the master!
[GASPS]
But the fat Hobbit, he knows.
Eyes always watching.
Then we stabs them out.
Put out his eyeses
and make him crawl.
Yes. Yes. Yes.
Kill them both.
Yes. No! No!
It's too risky. It's too risky.
SAM:
Where is he?
Where has he gone?
Hey, Gollum!
Where are you?
FRODO: Smeagol?
We could let her do it.
Yes. She could do it.
Yes, precious, she could.
And then we takes it
once they're dead.
Once they're dead.
Shh.
Come on, Hobbits.
Long ways to go yet.
Smeagol will show you
the way.
Follow me.
[***]
[THUNDER RUMBLING]
* Where once was light *
* Now darkness falls *
* Where once was love *
* Love is no more *
* Don't say goodbye *
* Don't say
I didn't try *
* These tears we cry *
* Are falling rain *
* For all the lies
You told us *
* The hurt, the blame *
* And we will weep *
* To be so alone *
* We are lost *
* We can never go home *
* So in the end *
* I'll be what I will be *
* No loyal friend *
* Was ever there for me *
* Now we say goodbye *
* We say you didn't try *
* These tears you cry *
* Have come too late *
* Take back the lies *
* The hurt, the blame *
* And you will weep *
* When you face the end alone *
* You are lost *
* You can never go home *
* You can never go home **
[***]